<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The truth and excellence of the Christian religion, with the corruptions and additions of the Romish Church a discourse, wherein the pre-eminence of Christianity is demonstrated above the religion of Jews or heathens, and the contradiction of popery to its main articles : and that religion prov'd in many instances to be a mixture of heathenish superstitions, and Jewish ceremonies : with a short vindication of Christian loyalty, and a brief historical account of Romish treasons and usurpations, since the Reformation / by a hearty professor of Reformed Catholick Christianity.</title>
            <author>S. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12365463</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12365463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 650:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The truth and excellence of the Christian religion, with the corruptions and additions of the Romish Church a discourse, wherein the pre-eminence of Christianity is demonstrated above the religion of Jews or heathens, and the contradiction of popery to its main articles : and that religion prov'd in many instances to be a mixture of heathenish superstitions, and Jewish ceremonies : with a short vindication of Christian loyalty, and a brief historical account of Romish treasons and usurpations, since the Reformation / by a hearty professor of Reformed Catholick Christianity.</title>
                  <author>S. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 141, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Gellibrand ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The dedication signed: S.C.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to S.C. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUTH and EXCELLENCE OF THE Chriſtian Religion, WITH THE CORRUPTIONS and ADDITIONS OF THE ROMISH CHURCH: A Diſcourſe, Wherein the Pre-eminence of Chriſtianity is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated above the Religion of <hi>Jews</hi> or Heathens; and the Contradiction of Popery to its main Articles: And that Religion prov'd in many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to be a mixture of Heatheniſh Superſtitions, and Jewiſh Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort Vindication of Chriſtian Loyalty: And a brief Hiſtorical Account of Romiſh Treaſons and Uſurpations, ſince the Reformation.</p>
            <p>By a hearty Profeſſor of Reformed Catholick Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd for the Benefit of thoſe that have not leiſure to read larger Volumes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Gellibrand</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Sir <hi>Thomas Roberts,</hi> Knight and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet of <hi>Glaſſenbury</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAVING been for ſome time no uncompaſſionate obſerver of the ſtrangely unnatural hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian jars of Proteſtants one with another; I was willing to divert my thoughts from ſo melancholly a Scene, and direct my Zeal againſt thoſe more dangerous Enemies of our Peace, Popery and Irreligion. I was willing to call off my
<pb facs="tcp:60423:3"/>
Native Country-men from biting and devouring one another, to unite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe potent Adverſaries, which are coming in upon us, through thoſe wide Breaches our Diviſions have made. And methinks, if men would but give themſelves leave to conſider how their hot Diſputes about Trifles, expoſe their Religion to the ſeorn of the Hectoring Atheiſts, and Deriſion of the bold Incendiaries of <hi>Rome;</hi> they would be leſs eager about Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Modes of Worſhip, and more induſtrious in an unanimous Defence of the common Principles of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I know many excellent Worthies have labour'd before me in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and adorn'd their Diſcourſes with all the Beauites of Wit, Learning, and Eloquence; but yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Irreligion gains new Proſelytes, and <hi>Rome</hi> ſwells big with greater hopes of once more introducing its blind Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions
<pb facs="tcp:60423:3"/>
into our Land, I have adventur'd at the ſame time, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the excellency of Chriſtianity againſt the Infidel, and arm my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men againſt the bold Corruptions of <hi>Rome;</hi> and tho I am not able to bear the Helmet of <hi>Saul,</hi> and his weighty Coat of Mail be too heavy for my Shoulders; tho I pretend not to ſuch ſtrong Lines, and nervous Arguments, as have been produc'd by the great Defenders of the Chriſtian and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Faith in our Age; Yet I know not, but a Sling and a Stone, even in the hand of a Stripling, may, by Divine Aſſiſtance in ſome meaſure prevent the increaſe of our Enemies, and confirm the ſtaggering among us, in the profeſſion, and practice of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Religion.</p>
            <p>And when once I had reſolv'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe Papers to the Cenſure of the World; I at the ſame time reſolv'd to make this publick acknowledgment
<pb facs="tcp:60423:4"/>
of the endearing Obligations you, Sir, have laid upon me. I must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Preſent is too mean for ſo great a Perſon; and 'tis a Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſo worthy a Name to prefix it before ſo inconſiderable a Piece; but your good Nature is ſuch, that I hope your Affection will bribe your Judgment; and what your Reaſon diſallows, your undeſerv'd reſpect to the Author will not condemn.</p>
            <p>I know, Sir, the uſual Flattery of <hi>Dedicatory Epiſtles;</hi> but know as well, that you hate the fawning of mean Paraſites; and had rather be good, than<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be magnifi'd as ſuch in the World; and tho I might expatiate in your due Praiſes, yet I will not ſo far treſpaſs upon your Humility (that great Ornament of your Nature, as well as Religion) but rather turn my Panegyricks into Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, That greatneſs and real goodneſs may be in you conjoin'd, and the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of your Birth may be equall'd by
<pb facs="tcp:60423:4"/>
the noble Endowments of your mind. Go on, Sir, in your hearty Zeal for God and Religion; and let your great Example prevent the boaſts of the bold Hectors of this Age, That they have Proſely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed all the Gentry of the Land. Let your Dependents and Neighbours be aw'd into Seriouſneſs by your ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy life; and allure men into the practice of Religion, by your ſincere compliance with the amiable Virtues it recommends. Let not the Infidel be able to ſay, <hi>That Religion is only fit for the Cells of melancholly Souls, and the retirements of the poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed Men in Black, who make it their Trade and Profeſſion;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, Sir, a glorious inſtance, How well Religion becomes the moſt noble Souls; and that Virtue is the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, and the higheſt badg of Honour. Continue, Sir, in your becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Zeal againſt Papal Corruptions, which ſo naturally tend to Debauchery
<pb facs="tcp:60423:5"/>
and Irreligion. And if this Diſcourſe may be any way uſeful for ſo excellent a purpoſe, I ſhall have great reaſon to bleſs God, for directing me to ſuch a Subject, Who am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Oblig'd, Humble, Affectionate Servant, S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60423:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ACTS XVII. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Theſe that have turned the world upſide down, are come hither alſo.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Juſt Vindication of the Chriſtian Religion from the impious Slanders of its profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and covert practices of its pretended Friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath in all Ages of the Church, been a very neceſſary work. For tho our Religion be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly atteſted, and God hath given convincing Evidences that it came from him; tho the excellency, and intrinſick worth of the Precepts, recommend it to the Approbation of all mankind. Tho the Doctrines it deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are highly agreeable to the wiſeſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of men, no way unbecoming a God to ſpeak, or men to hear. Tho no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the World was ever ſo admirably
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60423:6"/>
ſitted to advance the intereſt of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, or promote the advantage of publick Societies; yet hath it been vilely miſrepreſented by its Adverſaries, and the malice of Earth and Hell hath been buſied in inventing lying Accuſations, to prevent its ſettlement and Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed Author of it, was accus'd as a Blaſphemer and Impoſtor, tho he came upon the moſt admirable deſign; of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the happineſs of mankind, and laid down ſuch excellent Rules, as would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have fill'd the World with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of a flouriſhing Peace, and laſting Proſperity; yet was he traduc'd as a Troubler of the World, and Seducer of the People: and tho he deſerv'd to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the moſt profound reſpect, and recompenc'd with the beſt rewards; yet had he no other Crown than one of Thorns; and no other Throne than a Croſs. And the ſame Spirit that murder'd their Lord, did appear alſo againſt his Diſciples and Followers. Whereever they went to Preach the Word of the Kingdom, they were ſtill perſecuted with the bold lies, and virulent ſlanders of their enraged Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The Magiſtrates were excited to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the publick Peace, againſt theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60423:6"/>
Diſturbers of it. And thus they bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry out in the Text, <hi>Theſe that have turn'd the world upſide down, are come hither alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding which words, it will be neceſſary, briefly to reflect upon the Context.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> having travell'd<note place="margin">v. 1.</note> through many parts of <hi>Aſia,</hi> publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel; in this Chapter, are come to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> where was a Synagogue of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Heathen <hi>Greeks,</hi> and thoſe<note place="margin">v. 2.</note> call'd devout, <hi>i. e.</hi> Proſelytes of the Gate, that diſown'd the Follies and Superſtitions of the vulgar Heathen, worſhip'd one God, and complied with the ſeven Precepts of the Sons of <hi>Noah.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives the preference to his own Nation, and according to his uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cuſtom in other places, goes into the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue, and for three ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive<note place="margin">v. 3.</note> Sabbaths, reaſon'd with them, and proves by their Law, That Jeſus muſt be the expected <hi>Miſſiah.</hi> And his<note place="margin">v. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Arguments were ſo covincing, that he gain'd ſome converts among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and proſelyted a numerous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Religious <hi>Greeks.</hi> But thoſe<note place="margin">v. 5.</note> who remain'd obſtinate in their infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60423:7"/>
being fill'd with rage, gathered together a Rabble of the baſer ſort, and tumultuouſly throng to the houſe of <hi>Jaſon,</hi> whoſe Gueſt St. <hi>Paul</hi> was, and would forcibly have drag'd the Apoſtles before the Civil Magiſtrate; but they having prudently declin'd their fury, <hi>Jaſon</hi> with ſome other Converts is hal'd before the Rulers of the City, and accus'd as an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer<note place="margin">v. 6.</note> of Traytors, or at leaſt Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the publick Peace. For they cry out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe that have turn'd the world upſide down, are come hither alſo: Whom Jaſon hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe</hi>) they ſpeak concerning the Apoſtles, theſe whom <hi>Jaſon</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That have turn'd the world upſide down.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> word is, as I remember, us'd but once more in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and there it is rendred <hi>to trouble,</hi> Gal. 5. 12. <hi>I wiſh they were even cut off which trouble you,</hi> i. e. unſettle your minds, and ſeek to pervert you by teaching that new Doctrine of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and keeping the Ceremonial part of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law. The word properly ſignifies to Diſorder, Diſquiet, and raiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60423:7"/>
Confuſion. So that the Accuſation againſt the Apoſtles, may be underſtood either more Generally, or Particularly.</p>
            <p>1. More Generally; So the Accuſation may be, Theſe that have diſturb'd the World, by bringing in a new Religion, that have overturn'd the Ancient Religions; and brought in new Doctrines, directly oppoſite to the former; as if they ſhould have ſaid, <hi>They propagate new Principles, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of the Ancient Religion of us</hi> Jews, <hi>and cuſtomary rites of you</hi> Gentiles; <hi>they have in every place argued againſt that Law, which we are aſſured came down from Heaven; and laugh at that Worſhip which you account moſt ſacred and venerable. They have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly created diſturbance by this means, in other Cities; but with the ſame deſign,</hi> are come hither alſo; <hi>and therefore your duty to your Gods, obliges you to ſilence and reſtrain them; they indeed have eſcaped our hands, but we have brought theſe before you, who have given entertainment to their Perſons in their Houſes, and their Doctrines in their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. More Particularly, The Apoſtles may be here accus'd as diſturbing the World, by teaching Doctrines of Rebellion and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Indeed as they brought in a new Religion, they might be accounted Authors
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60423:8"/>
of Sedition, becauſe all Innovations were look'd upon as tending to unſettle the Peace of the State; but the more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar crime, of which they may here accuſe them, ſeems to be the immediate tendency of ſome of their Doctrines to Rebellion, and this is countenanc'd by the <hi>7th</hi> verſe; <hi>Theſe all do contrary to the decrees of</hi> Ceſar, <hi>ſaying there is another King, one Jeſus;</hi> we may therefore ſuppoſe the charge of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to be manag'd after ſuch a manner as this. <hi>Theſe that are the Peſts of Societies, and highly diſaffected to the eſtabliſh'd Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Friends of Anarchy, and Enemies to</hi> Ceſar; <hi>that maintain rebellious Principles, and ſow Sedition wherever they come; that have caſt off all ſenſe of Allegiance, and teach others to renounce their Subjection to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror; that will not obey the Laws themſelves, and perſwade others to refuſe their Obedience alſo, and preach up Subjection to another King, one Jeſus; theſe, as they have diſturb'd the Government in other Cities, ſo here alſo have they ſpread their Infection. Theſe are the men, theſe are their Principles; and whether they are worthy of reſtraint, judg ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus do the malicious <hi>Jews,</hi> miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Doctrines of theſe Meſſengers of Peace; and Innocence it ſelf was not a ſufficient Guard againſt the Perſecution of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60423:8"/>
their envenom'd Tongues. And, oh that I might ſay, concerning the whole Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World at this day, that ſuch an Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be Slanderous againſt them, as well as the Apoſtles; but alas! the Groans and Sighs of <hi>England,</hi> as well as other Lands, gives too ſad occaſion to cry out, <hi>Theſe that have turn'd the world upſide down, have come hither alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to the words in both theſe ſenſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeing they will well bear it, and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſuited to my deſign. In order to a more methodical Progreſs, I ſhall ſpeak to four Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Whether the Apoſtles did introduce a new Religion, different from what was before entertain'd in the World? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had the Divine Commiſſion to do ſo? For if they could produce the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God for what they did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they could not juſtly be blam'd or accus'd.</item>
               <item>2. Whether the Apoſtles Doctrine tended to Rebellion?</item>
               <item>3. Whether any profeſſed Chriſtians at this day, are juſtly liable to this charge in both ſenſes?</item>
               <item>4. I ſhall deduce ſuch Inferences as naturally reſult from the whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60423:9"/>1. Whether the Apoſtles did introduce a new Religion, and had a Commiſſion from God to do ſo?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer affirmatively; Chriſt did inſtitute, and his Apoſtles did publiſh a more perfect platform of Religion than was before exiſtent in the World; but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſufficient diſcoveries of Gods Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In this ſenſe, they did turn the World upſide down; taught Doctrines contrary to the univerſally receiv'd Opinions of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and darling Traditions and Practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Jews.</hi> The Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion did ſilence the <hi>Pagan</hi> Oracles where it prevail'd, and caus'd the Heathen <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons</hi> to fall down before it; the carnal Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the <hi>Jews</hi> were diſus'd, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was not able to ſtand before him, whom they call'd a Magician.</p>
            <p>The Brutiſh rites of the Heathens were aboliſh'd at the appearance of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and the Light of the Goſpel diſpers'd the Shadows of the Law, and took off the vail from <hi>Moſes.</hi> The Impurities of the Heathen, and Imperfection of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Worſhip, did render a more perfect Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divine will very neceſſary; and this was the Province undertaken by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60423:9"/>1. The Chriſtian Religion hath given a more compleat diſcovery of the Nature of God, and the manner how he will be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped</p>
            <p>The Conceptions of the Heathens, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Nature of God, were very groſs and confus'd; and the Wiſe-men of <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> were at continual jars and diſagreement about his Attributes; and they entertain'd very lame and imperfect, and ſome blaſphemous and unworthy No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of him. They did indeed generally acknowledg there could be but one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme and Sovereign God; and of him, <hi>Varro</hi> tells us, they made no Images and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures at <hi>Rome,</hi> till 170 Years after the Building of that City; but afterwards they carv'd him out in Wood and Stone, and ſtill worſhip'd inferior Deities with the ſame external reverence they paid to their <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> To th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe they dedicated Temples, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Altars, burnt large portions of Incenſe, and ador'd with the ſame out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward expreſſions of Devotion; and thus they debaſed his Infinite Power, as if he needed a rabble of petty pigmy Deities to rule the World. To him the common people (being influenced by the tales of the wanton Poets) Aſcrib'd the moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormous Vices, the Murders and Adulteries,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60423:10"/>
Sodomies and Rapes, which are related of '<hi>Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Crete,</hi> were appli'd by them to him whom they call'd Supreme. And tho many Philoſophers entertain'd more refind Notions, yet they dared not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the vulgar Follies, without incurring the Odium of the Rabble, and join'd in the ſame Rites and vile Ceremonies, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the ſame Cuſtoms with them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed among the common people reaſon was debas'd below common ſenſe; the idle Fables of their iuſtful Poets, were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily receiv'd. <hi>Orvids Metamorphoſis,</hi> and <hi>Homers Iliads,</hi> and the Divine Theology of the great <hi>Virgil,</hi> were their Syſtems of Divinity. The vileſt of men, who deſerv'd publick Puniſhment on Earth, were ador'd as Gods in Heaven; and thoſe whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories ought to be loath'd and deteſted, were reverenc'd with Divine Adoration; in ſome places they worſhip'd bruit Beaſts, Cows and Dogs were deifi'd, Serpents and Crocodiles were devoutly ador'd, Apes and Monkeys receiv'd their ſubmiſſive Proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſo that it was very queſtionable, which were more ridiculous, the gods or their worſhippers. The Sun, Moon, and Stars, Rivers and Elements, the Fruits of their Trees, Flowers in their Gardens, Herbs in their Fields, and the vileſt inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60423:10"/>
things in nature, were the objects of their religious worſhip; they paid a Divine Veneration to the Diſeaſes of their Bodies, the Paſſions of their Minds, and the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of their Lives.</p>
            <p>Nay, further, the curſed Fiends of Hell were treated with awful Reverence; and the ſworn Enemies to mankind had Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Altars conſecrated to their honour; thus vile were the Gods they ador'd, and the Rites wherewith they worſhip'd them, were equally abominable. What were the Myſteries of their Religion, but mixtures of the moſt extravagant folly and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Their <hi>Eleuſinia, Sacra, Floralia,</hi> and <hi>Bacchanal</hi> Solemnities, were compos'd of Antick tricks, and ſuch pieces of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as cannot be ſpoken without a bluſh, nor thought of without polluting the mind with immodeſt <hi>Idea's.</hi> What more Fantaſtick, than their Auguries by the flight of Birds, Preſages by the ſmoak of Incenſe, Fat of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Intrails of Beaſts, and all the other Charms and Sorceries in their Worſhip? theſe were the Notions the <hi>Gentiles</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd of God; this was the Worſhip they paid unto him; but the Chriſtian Religion overturn'd the whole Fabrick of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, demoliſh'd their Altars, ſilenc'd their Oracles, brake down their Images, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60423:11"/>
ſhew'd them the Folly and Superſtition, of which they had been ſo long guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>A Religion that gives us the beſt and moſt compleat Character of the Divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes; and repreſents him as a Being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinitely perfect, in whom all the ſcatter'd excellencies of the creatures are concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, without any of their Imperfections. A Religion that declares the Greatneſs of his Majeſty, the Infinity of his Power, the unſearchableneſs of his Wiſdom, the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riability of his Truth, the Purity of his Nature, and Boundleſneſs of his Goodneſs. A Religion which gives us the moſt lovely Deſcription of his Nature, and naturally tends to work in us the moſt awful reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and lowly humility, ſilial fear and dependent confidence, the moſt ardent Love, and unſpotted Purity, chearſul Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to every Command, and ready Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to every Providence. A Religion, whoſe Myſteries are grave and ſerious, becoming the Solemnities of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, without any mixtures of folly and prophaneneſs. A Religion which declares Gods ſevere Indignation againſt Sin, and love to vertue and goodneſs, and ſtrictly charges us to imitate the Divine Purity, and thus become partakers of a Divine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60423:11"/>
Nature. And now no wonder that ſuch a diſcovery as this, was a terrible Alarm to that World that lay in wickedneſs. No wonder that they who could injoy their Luſts without controul, and plead the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their gods, in juſtification of their crimes; were ſo hotly enrag'd againſt ſuch as gave them a quite contrary diſcovery of the Divine Nature. The light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel was hateful to them, who were unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be rous'd from their pleaſing Slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and had rather have continued in their deluſions. Thus were the Apoſtles diſturbers of the Heathen World by recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their groſs Apprehenſions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nature of God, and calling them from Worſhipping they knew not what, to the Service of the only living and true God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> indeed had clearer diſcoveries of Gods Nature; to them were committed his Oracles; and in <hi>Judah</hi> was his name known; But they had not ſuch clear and ſatisfying light, as we injoy under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; they ſaw his back - parts only, but we behold his Face. To them he was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd through a darkning veil, but to us through a more perſpicuous Glaſs. His confining the ſpecial Teſtimonies of his Love, to ſuch a narrow ſpot of Ground as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60423:12"/>
               <hi>Judea,</hi> did ſeem to repreſent him leſs ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and diffuſive in his goodneſs, than WE have reaſon to apprehend him. His ſo rigidly inſiſting on ceremonial Services, and poſitive Inſtitutions, and connivence at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Breaches of moral Duties, ſuch as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy,</hi> Divorces upon light occaſions, and the Laws of Retaliation and Revenge, did tend to beget a leſs awful ſenſe of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Purity than is due unto him. In the Chriſtian Religion; the Divine Wiſdom is diſplai'd in more lively Colours; the Divine Goodneſs is written in more legible Characters; his hatred to Sin, his love to Piety, is more perſpicuouſly diſcover'd. Never was there ſo lovely a Manifeſtation of all his Attributes, as in the Redemption of the World by our Saviour; the vaſtly extended Heavens, and all the beauteous ſplendid Lights that thence dart down their Influences on the World, and all the Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of Divine Power and Wiſdom, which may be ſeen upon the Earth, and all the admirable Acts of Providence, whereby God hath ſtartled his Enemies, or ſav'd his People; afford not ſuch exalted diſcoveries of the Divine Wiſdom, and Omnipotence, as is legible in the Incarnation, Life and Death of our Saviour. The deluge of the old World, the Flames of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60423:12"/>
Plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and all the Tremendous Judgments recorded in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> were not ſo ſenſible a Declaration of Gods Indignation againſt Sin, as the anguiſh and direful Agonies of the Lord Jeſus. The miracles of Mercy extended to <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and all the other Worthies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> give us not ſuch elevated tranſporting Apprehenſions of the depths of Divine Love, as may be drawn from the conſideration of that great My ſtery of Godlineſs, God manifeſted in the Fleſh. All the Declarations of Divine Perfections, that ever were vouchſaf'd to the World, come infinitely ſhort of theſe gracious diſcoveries in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Beſides the manner whereby the <hi>Jews</hi> Worſhip'd God (tho he in that Infant ſtate of the Church, for wiſe reaſons was pleas'd to inſtitute it) yet was it too groſs and carnal, and not enough ſuted to his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al nature; it conſiſted in gay Shows, and pompous Solemnities; in the Circumciſion of the Fleſh, Smoke of Sacrifices, Steams of Incenſe, Purgations from ceremonial Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Diſtinctions of Days, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and Meats; things that had no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick Goodneſs or worth to commend them. They had indeed a ſpiritual ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but the veil of Ceremonies was ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60423:13"/>
thick, and their Affections ſo carnal that very few div'd into their Typical meaning; but Chriſtianity teaches a Worſhip more admirably adapted to the Nature of God, and reaſon of man. <hi>The law came by Moſes, but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 1. 17. Grace in oppoſition to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal ſeverities; and Truth in oppoſition to their Types and Shadows. <hi>God is a ſpirit, and will be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth,</hi> Joh. 4. 24. not with carnal Ceremonies, but ſpiritual Affections; not with typical Shadows, but true and ſincere Devotions. The Rites of this Religion are but few in number, and therefore far leſs painful and laborious: Euchariſtical and Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of what is paſt, and therefore more apt for the inſtilling Piety, than thoſe typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Ordinances whoſe ſignification was more dark and obſcure. In this ſenſe 'tis acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd the Apoſtles did diſturb the World.</p>
            <p>2. The Apoſtles taught the only ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing method of mans Reconciliation with his Maker.</p>
            <p>This was a thing that very much puzled the conſidering part of mankind; and their Opinions were very different concerning it; the light of Nature taught them that they were Gods ſubjects, and that an entire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60423:13"/>
to him was their Duty; they knew that Sin was an affront to his Majeſty, and injury to all his Attributes; and the ſtings of Conſcience forcd thom to confeſs, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liad been very foulty in their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and incur'd the juſt Diſpleaſure of Heaven; and yet by Gods forbearance; they diſcern'd his readineſs to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd. His continuing forfeited Benefits diſcoveu'd, that he was not willing to puniſh them according to their Demerits.</p>
            <p>But how this Clemency and Mildneſs could be conſiſtent with his Holineſs, this very much perplex'd them. How he could preſerve the rights of his Juſtice, and yet give ſuch large Demonſtrations of his Goodneſs, this they could not apprehend. Some there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faſhion'd a God altogether like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and made the Poetick Fables the Rule of their Faith; the Tales of the Rapes, Adulteries, and ſecret amours of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Deities, confirm'd them in their Sins, and thought that to Sacrifice their Lives to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> or dye the Martyrs of <hi>Venus,</hi> would be anv leaſt no way diſpleaſing to Heaven. Others conceiv'd, that God took no notice, of ſmaller faults, and was not much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd at any crimes that brought no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table detriment to the Common-wealth. Others invented numerous expiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60423:14"/>
and multipli'd ſuperſtitious Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hoping by theſe little things to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the anger of God. For tho, perhaps, the way of Sacrificing was inſtituted by God, and convey'd throughout the World by Tradition from <hi>Noah;</hi> yet they unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably reſted in the Sacrifice it ſelf, never imagin'd it meerly typical, but vainly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd the Blood of Lambs would waſh away their crimes; tho they were utterly deſtitute of their Innocence. In caſes of extream diſtreſs, and to ſecure them from publick threatned Judgments, they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Gods with humane burnt Offerings, as if one Sin might be expiated by another of a deeper dye; but ſome were diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd with this method alſo, and agreed that the Supreme God delights rather in the Oblations of a pure mind, than in coſtly Incenſe, or burnt Offerings.</p>
            <p>Others therefore, eſpecially the proud Philoſophers, were ſo little ſenſible of their Obligation to God, that they thought their good works would recompence for the ſins they committed, and their ſhadows of virtue overballance their offences. Others had ſome apprehenſions of the neceſſity of a Mediator, and therefore to Angels and Deifi'd men (who had been publick Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors to their Country while they liv'd)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60423:14"/>
they addreſs'd themſelves, and brib'd them with Divine honours, to intercede with God on their behalf. This was a Doctrine generally entertain'd at <hi>Athens,</hi> in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time. In this Chapter we find, that when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preach'd Jeſus and the Reſurrection, they ſay, he ſeemeth to be a ſetter forth of ſtrange Gods or <hi>Demons;</hi> this was the title they gave to their Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Theſe ſeveral methods were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd by the Heathens, to reconcile God to man; but ſtill they were very fluctuating and dubious in their Opinions; and their guilty fears made them tremble, leſt after all their thoughtful pains they ſhould have miſtaken the right method, and God ſhould be ſtill unreconcil'd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> indeed had many Sacrifices that were Originally deſign'd to typifie and prefigure the Death of our Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; and the high Prieſts entring into the Holy of Holies once a year, repreſented his Interceſſion; but theſe ſhadows were ſo obſcure, and their eyes ſo dim, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few underſtood their ſpiritual ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They generally look'd for a glorious <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that ſhould Tranſlate the Empire from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> tread upon the Necks of their Enemies, and reign over the whole Earth with an outward magnificence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60423:15"/>
greater than that of <hi>Solomon.</hi> The Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples themſelves laboured under the ſame miſtake, and never dream'd of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch an Ignominious Death as our Saviour ſuffer'd. Hence when he was tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them what Sufferings he muſt undergo, St. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>How</hi> of thoughtfulneſs, <hi>Page 64.</hi>
               </note> very gravely rebukes him, ſaying, Maſter favour thy ſelf, this ſhall not be unto thee: it was not meerly his concern for his Maſter, but what would become of his own deſigns and hopes, that drew forth thoſe Expreſſions. Chriſt had promis'd him the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven which he knowing to be the <hi>inſignia</hi> of great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Princes Courts, interpreted it of ſome ſecular Greatneſs in the Kingdom of the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> And this made him ſo ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, when our Lord ſpake of Suffering and Death; and for this reaſon our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our calls him Satan, the name of the Uſurping God of this World; who had yet too much Power over him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 22, 23. So alſo <hi>Zebedees</hi> Children deſired one to ſit at his right hand, and the other at his left, as Perſons next in Dignity to him, in that earthly Kingdom they expected; and when his Death came, they then began to deſpair, ſaying, we hop'd that this <hi>had been
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60423:15"/>
he which ſhould have redeemed Iſrael,</hi> Lu. 24. 21. Thus we ſee the Diſciples themſelves, little expecting this way of Redemption re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veald in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>'Jews</hi> indeed, eſpecially the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> had generally very high thoughts of their own worth, and external Priviledges, as being <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and Gods peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar inheritance; believ'd their good works meritorious, accounted an external Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Law, as much as was requir'd, and ſaw little or no uſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; the righteous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. 7.</note> needing no repentance, ſeems to be ſpoken with ſome Reflection on their proud conceits. If at any time they did break the Law, they hop'd to be ſav'd from puniſhment, by the <hi>Opus operatum</hi> of a Sacrifice; and were ſo unreaſonably vain, as to think that the Blood of Bulls and Goats would waſh away their Sin. Hence the Apoſtle is forc'd ſo laboriouſly to prove, that all men being Sinners, there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to be reconcil'd to God, than by the method laid down in the Goſpel, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans;</hi> and that the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices under the Law, were only available as Typical of the great Propitiation of our Lord Redeemer; in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Thus abſur'd and dangerous no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60423:16"/>
did the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> entertain concerning the way to recover the Divine favour; and Chriſtianity did in this ſenſe alſo diſturb the World, by beating down their proud conceits, and clearly diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vileneſs of their ſins, by declaring that we are all Rebels againſt the King of Heaven; that he is ſo infinitely Pure and Holy, and we have rendred our ſelves ſo baſe and unworthy, that all our Services will be no way available without an expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice; and that, the moſt precious that Heaven or Earth could afford, even the Blood of his own beloved Son; and that he will not liſten to a Prayer from our guilty mouths, except it be hallow'd and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by the hands of this ſpotleſs and only-prevailing Mediator. The Chriſtian Religion hath brought to light that Myſtery hid from Ages, God incarnate. And what was puzling and obſcure before, to the moſt inquiſitive Philoſopher, is clearly unfolded in this Inſtitution. Now we need no more be held in Bondage and doubtful ſuſpence, but may aſſure our ſelves. That if we obey the Lord Jeſus as our King, depend upon him as our Prieſt, and ſincerely follow the rules of Life he hath laid down as our Prophet; in one word, if we heartily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the terms of the new Covenant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60423:16"/>
ſeal'd in his Blood, we ſhall obtain the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſins, the favour of God, and the rewards of eternity.</p>
            <p>3. The Apoſtles preſcrib'd the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and certain rules of Life.</p>
            <p>The Heathens were only directed by the dim light of Nature; and tho they might have ſpelt out the principal parts of their Duty, by viewing the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and the other works of God: Tho many excellent Leſſons of Morality are laid down by ſome inquiſitive Philoſophers; Yet they were ſo much biaſs'd by their vicious Inclinations, that they generally rejected them; the power of their Corruption was ſo great, and the encouragements to ſupport Religion, ſo weak and uncertain, that few were influenc'd by the moſt ſubſtantial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of any of their Philoſophers.</p>
            <p>The Duties of Piety towards God were commonly neglected. For while ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd his Being, others his Providence; While ſome confin'd him to the Heavens, others thought that at moſt he only minded the great concerns of Kingdoms and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicks below: While ſome doubted his love to mankind, and repreſented him as an auſtere Tyrannical Being; and others limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Power, and thought him unable to rectifie the evil Diſpoſitions of our Nature:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60423:17"/>
While ſome diſputed his Holineſs, and faſhion'd to themſelves an impure Deity; and others deni'd his Juſtice, and laugh'd at the Puniſhments of another World, as Bugbears, and Scare-crows, and painted Fires<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> While theſe Notions, and many more of the like tendency, were ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally entertain'd; how could it be poſſible, they ſhould pay that reverence and awful fear, that love and gratitude unto him, that he deſerves? Nor were they leſs defective in the great Duties of Morality, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Honeſty: They imbraced opinions that directly thwarted all the Duties of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table, and their Actions were too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with their Principles. Revenge was the character of a generous Soul: and to paſs by an injury, was the ſign of a cowardly Spirit. Self-murder was commended as an act of Heroical bravery, and made the common practice of the higheſt pretenders to Wiſdom. Adultery, Inceſt, and the crying ſin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> were allow'd by their gods, practic'd in their Temples, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by many of their Philoſophers. Rapine and Theft was encourag'd by the <hi>Spartans</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> as the matter of their Glory not of their ſhame. In a word, Religion was generally accounted a politick contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to keep the World in aw: and Virtue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60423:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and Vice were eſteemed as bare names, and no otherwiſe regarded, than as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or Prohibited by their reſpective Kings and Governours. Indeed ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers did give them better Inſtructions; but they themſelves were generally either very dubious, or ſwai'd ſo much by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Education, Intereſt, and their own habitual Luſts, that they led not much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lives than other men; as if their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts were intended only for Speculation, and the entertainment of their mind, and no way for practice, and the improvement of the Life. And at the firſt appearance of Chriſtianity, the World was arriv'd at an unuſual height of Debauchery. The Court of <hi>Rome</hi> had loſt all its former Virtue and Integrity, and was wholly drown'd in Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury and Wantonneſs. <hi>Epicurus</hi>'s Philoſophy was in greateſt Reputation, and men Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died nothing ſo much as how to improve their bruitiſh Pleaſures, to the utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance of injoyment; and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions follow'd the manners of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, and imitated the then Miſtreſs of the World, and were encourag'd by their Governours, who generally rais'd their Fortunes by their eminency in villany and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60423:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>The <hi>Jews</hi> had a more compleat diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Gods Will. The Decalogue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in it a brief ſummary of the Law of Nature; but becauſe of the hardneſs of their hearts, God conniv'd at ſome practices, not ſo agreeable to his Will. Thus <hi>Poligamy</hi> was wink'd at, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorces upon flight occaſions permitted; the Laws of revenge were eſtabliſh'd: And ſo many ritual Obſervations injoin'd, that they were too mindful of them, and too neglectful of the weightier matters of the Law. They were very mindful of external Ceremonies, but forgot the practice of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Virtue and Religion; they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſoil themſelves with imaginary cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Pollutions; but wholly inſenſible of deeper moral defilements. They cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcis'd their Fleſh, but not their Hearts; and Sacrific'd their Beaſts, but not their bruitiſh Luſts. They us'd all poſſible diligence to cleanſe themſelves from the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of their Bodies, but took no care of the more dangerous ſpots on their Souls. They religiouſly abſtain'd from the meats ſorbidden in their Law; but made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſhunning the ſinful Pollutions, that were more to be avoided. And eſpecially, in our Saviours time, their Religion was dwindled away, and nothing but a lifeleſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60423:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhadow left. For one powerful Party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, the <hi>Sadducees,</hi> had taken away the belief of that great Bulwark of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without which it is hardly poſſible to ſubſiſt, The immortality of the Soul, and a future State. Another Sect, the <hi>Herodians,</hi> were Court-Flatterers, and State-Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who made it an act of their Religion to comply with the humours of their Prince Thoſe who pretended moſt to Sanctity and Piety, the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> had found an eaſie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which they fanci'd would pleaſe God and themſelves too, conſiſting moſtly in trifles and ſhadows, and very defective in the grear Duties of Religion; they had put corrupt gloſſes on the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and becauſe the Magiſtrate could only puniſh the outward act, they fondly preſum'd God as indulgent, and never imagin'd that their vain thoughts, or idle words, would be imputed to them as their ſins. They were indeed very careful to have a ſaint-like outſide, tho devilliſh Luſts dwelt within; and hop'd to be juſtifi'd and ſav'd, tho their hearts were never purifi'd, or amended. All their Religion lay in the Obſervations of ſome Traditions and Cuſtoms handed down from their forefathers. The Duties of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were ſuppli'd only by Ceremonious Services and Rites: they were abominably
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60423:19"/>
guilty of Deceit and Injuſtice, Cozenage, and Over-reaching one another; and neglected the Rules of Juſtice and common Honeſty among men; they knew no ſuch thing as a Spirit of Divine unbounded Charity; but were of very rugged, ſowr Diſpoſitions; they were ſwoln big with an high conceit of themſelves, and look'd with contempt and diſdain on the reſt of mankind: their Charity was contracted within the conſines of <hi>Judea;</hi> and they would not ſo much as eat with an uncircumcis'd <hi>Gentile</hi> or <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan,</hi> nor pay them the common Offices of Civilty. In a word, their righteouſneſs was ſo lam'd, and wofully imperfect, that our Saviour tells us it could qualifie no man for Heaven, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 20.</p>
            <p>Thus did the whole World lye in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and therefore no wonder that the ſtrictneſs of the Chriſtian Doctrine was ſo diſturbing to thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be freed from their pleaſing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes.</p>
            <p>A Doctrine, that requires we ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly reverence and adore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Divine Majeſty, and expreſs our Adoration by ſolemn Prayers, and Praiſes, and acts of Devotion. A Doctrine, that requires a flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love, an humble Dependence, an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fear, and careful imitation of every
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60423:19"/>
imitable Perfection; That we ſhould give him the Supremacy of our Affections, without any corrival or competitor; That we ſhould Worſhip him only in ſuch a manner, as is agreeable to the Dignity of his Nature, and Revelation of his Will; That we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſe his Name in a prophane irreverent manner, but always with that becoming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe, that is due to ſo Sovereign a Majeſty; That we ſhould ſanctifie that time he hath ſet a part for his Service, and then Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him with ſincere devout Affections; That we ſhould be Pure, and Chaſt, and Sober, and Temperate, and Humble; tame our Fleſh, ſubdue our Luſts, be moderate in our purſuit of worldly Injoyments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the World, entertain a mean Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelves, and all things here below: Sacrifice our ſecular Intereſts, and even life it ſelf, for the ſake of God and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and always behave our ſelves as the Citizens of Heaven: That we ſhould love our Neighbour as our ſelves, and not be ſo narrow-ſoul'd, as to contain our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in ſmaller bounds than thoſe of the Univerſe: That we ſhould follow Peace with all men, forgive our Enemies, pray for our Perſecutors, and be kind and obliging to all with whom we converſe: That we ſhould ſubdue all angry Reſentments, and quench
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60423:20"/>
all revengeful deſires, and carefully abſtain from every thing that is injurious to our Neighbour; and do to others as we ſhould reaſonably deſire they ſhould do to us, were we in their circumſtances. That we ſhould in order to theſe ends, repent of our Sins, believe in the Lord Jeſus, and depend upon the aids of Divine Grace, to enable us to purifie our thoughts and words, and purge our actions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it us for Heaven. Theſe are the chief heads of the Chriſtian Doctrine. Theſe are the excellent Rules which our Saviour commanded by his word and bleſſed example. Theſe were the Precepts that ſtartled the World, and inflam'd the hearts of guilty Sinners with ſuch hatred and malice againſt the Apoſtles. This was the chief cauſe of their enmity againſt the Preachers of this new Faith, even becauſe they would have reclaim'd them from their vicious courſes, and invited to the utmoſt heights of holineſs; becauſe they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to pull down the Devils throne, and eſtabliſh the Empire of Chriſt; to root up thoſe Weeds and Briars that had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run the Garden of God; and plant thoſe Seeds of Grace that might bring forth fruit unto righteouſneſs. Their deſign was to work in the hearts of men, an holy conformity to the Divine Nature; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60423:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Philoſophy of the Heathens, and Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was not ſo clear and perfect, as was neceſſary to bring men to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; therefore did God ſend his Son to give this laſt and moſt perfect Revelation of his Will; which for clearneſs, and certainty, and perfection, far exceeds all the Volumes of Morality compil'd by Heathens, and even that Law which was given from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe particulars, 'tis confeſſed, the Apoſtles did <hi>turn the world upſide down;</hi> but they were ſo far from deſerving a reproof, that for this very Cauſe the higheſt venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, (as the moſt noble Benefactors to mankind,) is their due. The error of the men of <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> who took them for gods in the ſhape of men, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 11. was much more excuſable than the dangerous miſtake of theſe who accuſed them for diſturbing a vicious World: For they teſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation to their Doctrines wherever they came.</p>
            <p>1: By their intrinſick Worth and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; they maintained none of the abſurd Articles of the Gentile Faith, and impoſed none of the burthenſom Ceremonies of the Jewiſh Worſhip; but their Doctrines were all ſuited to the Reaſons of men, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended themſelves to their approbation by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60423:21"/>
their intrinſick Excellence. To go over the former particulars:</p>
            <p>1. Their conceptions of God, and the manner how he will be Worſhipp'd. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tells us, that he who gave to all their Beings and Perfections, muſt be himſelf infinitely perfect: Muſt injoy all excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in himſelf in an eminent degree, and be diveſted of every Imperfection. The works of Nature declare that he muſt be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in Power, who created the vaſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of Heaven and Earth; incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in Wiſdom, who order'd every thing with ſuch admirable harmony and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and boundleſs in his Goodneſs, who gave ſuch comely Perfections to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and made them ſo uſeful and ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able one to another; the whole World is a Map to repreſent theſe ſeveral excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and every Creature a Herald to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim theſe glorious Perfections, his works of Providence diſcover his Juſtice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he Thunders againſt obſtinate Sinners; his Holineſs, whereby he ſhows his delight in the ſincerely Obedient; and his Truth, whereby he makes good his Promiſes and Threatnings. Indeed the Nature of God is Myſterious, and the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is Incomprehenſible to humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but yet it is not repugnant to it. The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60423:21"/>
Unity of the three Perſons of the Godhead, tranſcends indeed our conceptions, but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon connot prove it to be an impoſſibility, or to include a contradiction; for altho among creatures one nature is ſtill join'd with one ſubſiſtence; yet the Divine Nature being not of the ſame condition with created ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it can never be prov'd impoſſible that three Divine Perſons ſhould ſubſiſt in one Nature: the manner indeed is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible to reaſon; and it is not to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that a finite creature ſhould be able fully to comprehend an infinite being.</p>
            <p>In a word, The Chriſtian Religion gives us the moſt exalted lovely apprehenſions of the Divine Nature, without any of thoſe jarring notions which the Heathens entertained; and tho there be ſome myſteries in our Faith, yet they tend only to exalt God, and debaſe Man; and 'tis our duty to believe what God ſays of himſelf, and to fall down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip what we cannot comprehend.</p>
            <p>But further, the manner of worſhipping God preſcrib'd by the Apoſtles, is highly ſuitable to his Majeſty, and becoming his Spiritual Nature; not with the follies and extravagancies of the Heathens, nor pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous and gaudy Ceremonies of the <hi>Jews;</hi> but with a modeſt magnificence, and comely ſimplicity; with prayer and praiſe, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60423:22"/>
and other ſolemn exerciſes of Devotion; with a reverent celebration of its myſteries, without I dolatry or Superſtition on the one hand, and without contempt of a Being ſo worthy of the moſt humble adoration, on the other. This is the method of Devotion in the Chriſtian Church; much more comely and decent, and agreeable to the Nature of God, and Reaſons of Men, than the butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery of Sacrifices, and numerous gay ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities among the <hi>Jews,</hi> which except they, had prefigured the great undertakings of the Meſſiah, would never have been injoyn'd; Much more then the ridiculous charms, and impure rites of the Heathen Worſhip, which the wiſeſt among them were aſham'd of, and only join'd therein <hi>ut legibus juſſa non ut diis grata, as commanded by their laws, not as pleaſing to their Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Their Doctrine concerning mans recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God by the Lord Jeſus, tho it was above the ſphere of reaſon to invent, yet when once reveal'd; appears highly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to reaſon; for when man had wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully broke the Divine Law, and expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the threatned puniſhments of infinite juſtice; God, that he might ſignalize his mercy, and fill the hearts and mouths of Men and Angels with the moſt ardent love, and admiring Hallelujahs, was pleas'd to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60423:22"/>
diſpence with his threatning, and ſhow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ready to be reconcil'd. Now what imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable way can we think of, more agreeable to reaſon, whereby man may be reſtor'd to the divine favour? ſhall he meerly pardon ſinners? this clemency would be but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fooliſh pity: for it would argue, either that he wanted Power to effect what he threatned; or was defective in Wiſdom, as if he thought his law unadviſedly made, and foreſaw not the inconveniences it would occaſion: Or, that he was not infinite in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who could ſo eaſily be reconcil'd to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rebels. Beſides, this would weaken his Government over Angels and Men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to ſin for the future in hopes of the ſame mercy and compaſſion.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how unreaſonable it is to imagine God ſhould meerly pardon ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was neceſſary therefore that ſome ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſhould be made; and except this be proportionable to the offence, the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences will ſtill follow: the repute of the Law will not be kept up; God will ſtill labour under the diſhonourable reflections of Levity, Impotence, and Impurity; and Men will be encouraged to ſin for the future, with hopes of an eaſy remedy. This bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den was too weighty for the ſhoulders of any creature: ſuch is the Malignity of ſin,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60423:23"/>
and ſo: great a diſhonour to the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſty, that it is impoſſible the ſervices and ſufferings of a meer creature ſhould compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate for the affront. It was neceſſary that God. ſhould ſatisfy. Himfelf; and becauſe thoſe ſatisfactions do moſt ſecure the ends of ſatisfaction, which come as near the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned penalty as may be, 't was neceſſary he ſhould become man, live a life of miſery, and dye an accurfed death, and endure ſuch agonies and torments of Body and Soul, as might repreſent more livelyly to the ſons of men, what their ſins had deſerved, and come as near the penalty as the dignity and innocence of his Nature would permit. Thus Gods hatred of ſin is moſt clearly diſplay'd; and men are moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effectually deterr'd from continuance in any iniquity. Thus the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, and Power, and Holineſs, and Mercy, ſhine in their brighteſt luſtre, and conſpire together in a moſt admirable har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and agreement; and that men might ſtill be more apprehenſive of their own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God, not withſtanding all the wonders of his love, teſtifies his hatred to our ſins by refuſing to admit any immediate applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him; and reſolving to accept of no ſervices, nor hear any prayers that are not perfum'd by the interceſſion of his beloved Son. This is the admirable Goſpel-method
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60423:23"/>
of propitiating the Divine Favour, which we indeed dar'd not once to have thought of; till God had reveal'd it: but now it is made known, appears to be only ſatisfactory to reaſon. What the Sacrifices, and Offerings, and other contrived methods of ſatisfaction among the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> were too weak to effect; this, this is done by the great Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice of our Lord Redeemer.</p>
            <p>3. Their precepts and rules of Life were all reaſonable and advantagious to our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; conducive to the health of our bodies, the, tranquility of our minds, the peace of our conſciences, the ſweetning of our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, the exalting our natures, the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our eſtates, the advancement of our reputation, and the comfort of our lives. By the practiſe of them, we ſhall conſult our private intereſt, obtain the good will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of men, and promote the publick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of all. We ſhall act worthy of our ſelves, and becoming our reaſon; obtain the Divine Favour, and reſemble the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. What more comely and decent than a profound admiration of him, who is ſo Glorious and excellent in himſelf! An: ardent love of him who is ſo kind and beneficial to us! An awful reverence of him who is ſo Powerful, Holy, Wiſe, and Juſt! and a cheerful obedience to all his Laws,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60423:24"/>
who is our Soveraign and our Father, our Friend and beſt Benefactor! What more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable than prayer to him, who is able to ſupply our wants? and praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to the ſame God, who gives all the comforts of this life, and from whom we expect the rewards of a better? What more juſt, and fit, and conducible to our intereſt, than that we ſhould be upright in our dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with our neighbour, veracious in our words, faithful in our truſts, ſincere in our contracts, innocent and inoffenſive in our whole behaviour, avoiding every thing that may be to his prejudice; and uſing all means to oblige him, and further his welfare? What more reaſonable than that we ſhould be civil and courteous and good natur'd to all, and be ready to perform friendly offices to ſuch as beg or need our aſſiſtance? What more reaſonable than to be peaceable and orderly in our ſtations, obſervant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectſul to Superiors, meek and gentle to our inferiors, kind and familiar with our equals, modeſt and lowly, ingenuous and compliant in all our behaviour? There are ſecret charms in ſuch a converſation as this, which cannot but command the love and eſteem of all men. What more reaſonable than that reaſon ſhould have its due prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative within us? Not depreſs'd by a domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60423:24"/>
appetite, deluded by an enticing world, or ſeduc'd by a deceitful Devil? That we ſhould have a mean opinion of our ſelves ſuitable to our condition of weakneſs and dependence, ſin and folly; that we be ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in the uſe of the innocent comforts of this life, as no way to impair our health, corrupt our minds, ſtain our reputations, prejudice our peace, endamage our eſtates, or our lives. What more reaſonable than a generous contempt of theſe mean and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding injoyments, and an elevation of our thoughts and affections to that Heaven, where are objects more worthy our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, and only ſatisfactory to that Heavenly off-ſpring within us? What more reaſonable than to be ſorry for our paſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, and reſolve amendment? he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a love to his ſin, and reſolves to perſiſt in his rebellion, deſerves to die for his crimes, and to have no benefit by an offer'd pardon. What more reaſonable than to believe in the Lord Jeſus? and ſeeing he hath been ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate over us, to truſt in his Merits, obey his Laws, and comply with the terms of his Covenant?</p>
            <p>Theſe are the precepts our Religion boaſts of, as her Crown and Glory. Theſe are the ſubſtantial Rules we have reaſon to glory in; ſo admirably fitted to the Glory of God,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60423:25"/>
and the good of mankind; ſo friendly to human ſociety, and advantagious to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of every man in the world.</p>
            <p>Let the Heathens now ceaſe their boaſts of the wife Laws of <hi>Lycurgus, Solon,</hi> or <hi>Numa;</hi> for whatever was excellent in them, is more clearly laid down in the Laws of Chriſt, without any mixture of their imperſections. Let the <hi>Jews</hi> ceaſe their triumphs in the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> for behold a greater than <hi>Moſes</hi> is here. Thus it appears, that the Chriſtian Doctrine by its intrinſick worth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd its Divine Original, and by its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the image of Gods Holineſs, Wiſdom and Goodneſs, manifeſted from whence it proceeded.</p>
            <p>2. By the external teſtimonies God gave of his approbation.</p>
            <p>1. By propheſies. God had frequently foretold that he deſign'd to aboliſh that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal worſhip he had ſet up, and give a more compleat revelation of his will, more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his own Spiritual Nature, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men. That he would enlarge the bounds of his dominion; remove that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial worſhip which could only be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd in <hi>Judea;</hi> and that <hi>ſpiritual incenſe, and a pure offering ſhould be offered up in every place; and the gentiles</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould call upon him;</hi> That he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60423:25"/>
would raiſe up a Prophet like unto <hi>Moſes</hi> (who therefore muſt be a Law give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Mediator of a<note place="margin">Deut. 18. 15.</note> new Covenant, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was) and that he ſhould have Words, new Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions put into his Mouth; to him the People were obliged to hearken with Attention and Obedience. <hi>That God wòuld make a new Covenant with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31. 31.</note> 
               <hi>houſe of Iſrael,</hi> different from that made in <hi>Egypt.</hi> And would write his Laws, not upon Tables of Stone, but in their hearts, <hi>i. e.</hi> he would give them ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions as are eaſily diſcoverable by the light of nature; ſo that there would not be ſo much need of teaching every man his Neighbour, but every man ſhall eaſily underſtand his Duty. That the <hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4.</note> ſhould be aboliſh'd, and that of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> be eſtabliſh'd, which ſhould endure for ever. That a new Heaven, and a new Earth ſhould be created, a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more agreeable to Heaven, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to Earth. That the Ark of the Covenant ſhould be no more viſited; and God would ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer. 3. 16. Iſa.</hi> 66. 18, 21.</note> all Nations unto him, and out of them chuſe to himſelf Prieſts and Levites.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60423:26"/>
That the Deſir'd of all Nations ſhould come, and erect a ſpiritual Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Kingdom in the hearts of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 7.</note> men, to give them more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Laws, and reduce them to fuller Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and better Obedience. Thus was it Prophecy'd of old, that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Religion ſhould be aboliſh'd, and a more perfect Revelation ſubſtituted in its place. It is indeed ſaid of ſome of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bates.</hi> Of the Chriſtian Religion. <hi>page 78.</hi>
               </note> that they were to continue for ever, but that was only to diſtinguiſh them from ſome temporary Injunctions, that were of force only while they were in the Wilderneſs, or when they were Inhabitants of <hi>Canaan;</hi> but were to be practic'd in all places, till by a new ſignification of the Divine Will, they were forbidden. And it's obſervable, that in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, the word [<hi>for ever</hi>] doth oftentimes, only import a continuance to the Jubilee; ſo that theſe rituals were to continue till the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the great Jubilee of the World. Thus hath God declar'd his Abrogation of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Worſhip, and by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath further diſoblig'd us from the Obſervance of it; nay diſabled the moſt obſtinate Adherents to it, from performing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60423:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the chief Rites of their Religion. He hath demoliſh'd their Temple, confounded their Tribes, and forc'd them to wander for Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years without a Prieſt or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>Ephod</hi> or <hi>Teraphim.</hi> God hath aboliſh'd the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Worſhip, which he once al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd; and the Doctrine of the Apoſtles was only that compleat Revelation of the Divine Will, which was foretold by the Prophets of the Lord; and therefore theſe <hi>Jews</hi> had no reaſon to quarrel at the Apoſtles, as turners of the World upſide down.</p>
            <p>2. By Miracles, Tho the intrinſick Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of theſe Doctrines, and their being a completion of thoſe Prophecies which were long before publiſh'd to the <hi>Jews,</hi> were ſufficient Evidence of Gods Approbation; Yet becauſe the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by Miracles, and that dull People was hardly to be convinc'd any other way, becauſe a Religion ſo contrary to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſts, ancient Cuſtoms, inveterate Prejudices, and corrupt Inclinations of the Heathens, could hardly expect much more ſucceſs than the Precepts of their ſober Philoſophers, except the Power of God were diſplaid in ſome eminent ſurprizing manner. That men might be therefore render'd ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inexcuſable in their unbelief, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour by many miraculous works declar'd,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60423:27"/>
that the hand of God was with him. He outdid <hi>Moſes;</hi> before he diſplac'd him, and ſhow'd the pre-eminence of his Doctrine, by his more wonderful works. He was born of an immaculate Virgin, and honour'd by a miraculous Star. He was proclaim'd the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> by the Gratulations of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; and Worſhipp'd in his Cradle by the Wiſe-men of the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended on him at his Baptiſm, and a voice from Heaven (ſuch as perhaps had never been heard ſince the delivery of the Law) declar'd that he came as an extraordinary Agent from God. I know the <hi>Jews</hi> make their boaſts of many Voices from Heaven, which they call <hi>Bathcol,</hi> after the days of <hi>Malachi;</hi> but we may well account them Forgeries, or Diabolical Illuſions; for it is utterly unima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, That when Divine Vengeance had taken away viſion and prophecy, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediate revelations, he ſhould give this plain diſcovery of his will. The new Law of Chriſt, was therefore atteſted by the ſame way of evidence, with the old Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> Thus alſo at his transfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration, the ſamevoice in the<note place="margin">Luke. 17. 5.</note> preſence of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> comes from God with the addition of, <hi>Hear him;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, You have obey'd my ſervants <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> the inſtruments
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60423:27"/>
I chieſly us'd in eſtabliſhing the old Law; but now hear and obey my Son, and that full and compleat Law he ſhall promulge. This great atteſtation, if there were no other, would confirm the truth of Chriſtianity. But to go on; Angels Miniſter'd to him in his temptations; and he faſted even above the poſſibility of Nature; all ſorts of diſeaſes fled before him, and he cur'd more plagues than <hi>Moſes</hi> brought upon <hi>Egypt;</hi> Fevers, Palſy, Leproſy, Diſtractions, were heal'd by no Medicinal Applications, but meerly by a touch of his Hand, or word of his Mouth. He laid his Commands on the ſtormy winds, and they were obedient; and ſtill'd the rage of a tempeſtuous Sea. He ſatisfi'd the hunger of thouſands with almoſt nothing, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipli'd five Loaves and two Fiſhes to content a numerous multitude. He ſpake ſuch words as gave ears to the deaf; and looſend the tongue of the dumb to proclaim his divine commiſſion The touch of his Garment ſtop'd a flux of blood; and [<hi>I will, be thou clean</hi>] chas'd away a leprous defilement. <hi>Talitha Cumi,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd the Rulers Daughter to life; and the touch of a Bier converted the ſorrows of a funeral into mirth and gladneſs. <hi>Lazarus come forth,</hi> recover'd that dead that was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt putrifi'd in the grave; and, O <hi>woman great is thy faith, be it unto thee as thou wilt,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60423:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Cur'd the Canaanitiſh womans daughter that was poſſeſs'd, and at a great diſtance from him. The Devils were forc'd to ſlee with halte from the bodies of men, and tremblingly, acknowledg him to be the Son of God. Clay and Spittle, apt to ſtrengthen blindneſs, rather than take it away, gave ſight to him that was born blind; and by the moſt preternatural means, he wrought the moſt wonderful works. He foretold his own death, with all its tragical circumſtances, and predicted his own Reſurrection. The deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt, the Perſecution of his Diſciples, the Deſtruction of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the propagation of Chriſtianity, were all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by him; long before their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Earth was caſt into trembling Convulſions, the Rocks were rent, the Sun was Eclips'd, contrary to all the rules of Aſtronomy; and inſenſible Nature was caſt Into an Univerſal agony, as if it were indued with knowledg, at his Funeral.</p>
            <p>At the time appointed, he aroſe again, and numerous departed Saints with him. He convers'd with men for forty days on Earth, and was ſeen by 500 at once; at laſt he aſcended into Heaven before a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of admiring ſpectators; and did not vaniſh away on a ſudden, but went up with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60423:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all the ſolemnity and leiſure of a triumph; from thence he diſpens'd his gifts to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; inſpir'd a mean company of illiterate Fiſher-men with a ſpirit of prophecy and revelation, and gave them power of ſpeaking in many of thoſe languages which the curſe of <hi>Babel</hi> brought upon the world. They perform'd all ſorts of miracles by the bare uſe of his Name; and did ſuch mighty works as amaz'd all ſpectators. He turn'd a Wolf into a Lamb; and the bare words of [<hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me</hi>], chang'd a furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſecutor into a zealous convert. Theſe things were not done in a corner, but open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> In <hi>Jude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> where the beſt worſhip of God was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliiſh'd, and diabolical impoſtures moſt abhor'd. In <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Metroplis of that Nation. In their Synagogues, and publick aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, before his moſt inveterate and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate adverſaries; and yet none of theſe could deny the matter of fact, but out of envy and ill will, imputed them to Magick, and the aſſiſtance of the Devil. But alas! the nature of theſe works, ſo good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to man kind, and their deſign and tendency to pull down that dominion the Devil had ſo long uſurp'd, and plant that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in the hearts of Men, which is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Nature; clearly teſtify, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60423:29"/>
ſuch an accuſation could proceed from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but deviliſh envy and malice.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the credentials that Chriſt brought with him from Heaven.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the convincing Arguments that he was ſent from God.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the demonſtrations which over power'd the reaſons of men, diſpell'd that thick darkneſs which had ſo long over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the Earth, and ſo ſoon fill'd the world with the light and knowledg of the Goſpel; and therefore theſe <hi>Jews</hi> ought not ſo cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly to have accus'd the Apoſtles, but with joy and admiration to have flock'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſaying, Theſe Teachers ſent from God, that have reform'd the world, <hi>are come hither alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. Queſt. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles diſturb'd the world, by teaching Doctrines of Rebellion? For the ſenſe may be, Theſe that raiſe muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in every place, overturn</hi> Ceſars <hi>Authority, and Preach up Allegiance to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother King, one Jeſus,</hi> are come hither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p>Here my buſineſs is to prove, That Chriſtianity doth not deſtroy, but eſtabliſh and confirm that Duty which the Law of Nature challenges from Subjects to their Prince. Indeed the <hi>Jews</hi> were (of all men)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60423:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
moſt unjuſt in this accuſation. For the great reaſon of their malice againſt Jeſus, was, becauſe where as they expected a Meſſiah that ſhould break the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke, and deliver them from the Tyranny and oppreſſion of <hi>Ceſar;</hi> That ſhould Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them from their Vaſſalage to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumcis'd Emperor; and reign as a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious <hi>Monarch</hi> over the world: He diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed their proud expectations, came in a mean and humble manner; proclaim'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the true Meſſiah; and yet declar'd that his Meſſage was peace and not war; and that his Kingdom was Spiritual, and not of this world. If he would have aſcended the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and warr'd againſt the principalities and powers on Earth, inſtead of thoſe of Hell: If inſtead of raiſing up <hi>Lazarus</hi> and ſome meaner perſons, he would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to life their <hi>Sampſons</hi> and <hi>Joſhuas,</hi> and mighty men of valour; If inſtead of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the way to be ſav'd from eternal Miſery, he would have inſtructed them how to be freed from Earthly Bondage; and inſtead of bringing them news of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, he would have brought the more welcome tidings of that Kingdom on Earth they expected: Then they would have gladIy receiv'd him as the promis'd Meſſiah, the Son of God. But ſeeing he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60423:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his power another way, they miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent his Doctrine, ſlander his Perſon, Perſecute him to death as an enemy to <hi>Ceſar;</hi> and accuſe his followers as diſloyal perſons, and Authors of Rebellion. But that the Chriſtian Religion is no ſriend to diſloyalty, a very little ſearch will quickly determine; for obedience to Magiſtrates is very much urg'd, and Rebellion ſeverely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Goſpel. The great deſign of Chriſts coming into the world, was peace; To reconcile God to man, and men to one another. To ſubdue our paſſions, and calm our diſcontents. To pull down our pride, and abate our ſelfiſhneſs. To poliſh the roughneſs of our natures, and take away all thoſe impediments which would hinder our paying a due obſervance to ſuperiors. None of his Doctrines did ever infringe the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Power; but he perſwaded men to be ſubject, not only for wrath and fear of puniſhment, but out of a principle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and duty. Tho he was Univerſal King of the whole Creation, yet his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was no way deſtructive of the juſt rights of <hi>Ceſar.</hi> Tho he challeng'd Subjection to him from all his followers, yet he preſs'd both by precept and example a due ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Emperor alſo. The ſame mouth that commands <hi>to pay unto God the things
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60423:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that are Gods,</hi> requires us <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 12. 17.</note> alſo, <hi>to pay unto Ceſar the things that are Ceſar</hi>'s. He works a Miracle to pay the tribute-penny, which was either a tax impos'd by the <hi>Romans,</hi> or rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> for the uſe of the Temple. Either way he declares his ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Government. He commands his Diſciples to pray for their perſecutors, not to curſe and damn them; and gives them leave to fly from their rage, but not to oppoſe and reſiſt it. He hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the People, when they would have made him a King: and check'd his Diſciples when they vainly conteſted about priority, in that Earthly Kingdom they fondly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. He Rebuk'd <hi>Peters</hi> forward zeal for his Maſter, when he cut off <hi>Malchus</hi>'s Ear; and to prevent the Slanders of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, miraculouſly cur'd the injur'd perſon. Tho he could have commanded twelve Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Angels to his reſcue, yet he choſe rather to imploy them in meſſages of peace: and tho with thoſe Majeſtick words of [<hi>I am he</hi>] He could have ſtruck the Souldiers dead, as well as down to the earth: yet did he meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit without any reſiſtance; he went as a Sheep to the Slaughter, and as a Lamb he was dumb and open'd not his mouth. Tho his adverſaries bare manifeſt falſe-witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60423:31"/>
him, yet was he meek and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and the ſharpneſs of his pain extorted no paſſionate exclamations againſt the injury they had done him. But on the contrary, he forgot not his own precepts, but breath'd out that admirable prayer for them, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi> And his Diſciples did exactly imitate their Lord. And tho they liv'd among his enemies and their own, and met with injuries enough to have inflam'd their Spirits; yet they give us the ſame leſſons of peaceable ſubjection to the higher powers. Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> that is here accus'd, commands the <hi>Romans</hi> (tho living under <hi>Nero</hi> an <hi>Heathen,</hi> a Tyrant, a Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, and one of the moſt infamous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Nature) To be ſubject to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers, and render fear, honour, tribute, cuſtom to them. Nor was this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion only conſtrain'd through<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> the neceſſity of thoſe times, wherein they had not power to reſiſt, For, ſays he, <hi>we muſt needs be ſubject not only for wrath; but for conſcience ſake; and be that reſiſts, ſhall receive to himſelf damnation?</hi> And becauſe perhaps ſome ſeeds of Rebellion might begin in thoſe early days to be ſow'd by ſome Hereticks, the Apoſtle exhorts <hi>Titus,</hi> to put his converts<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 1.</note> in mind of their duty of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60423:31"/>
to principalities and powers. The ſame doctrine is urg'd by Saint <hi>Peter, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to every ordinance of man for the Lord ſake.</hi> Indeed the Chriſtian Religion is the beſt ſecurity to governours, of the obedience of their ſubjects. A diſloyal Chriſtian is a perfect contradiction. He can be no true friend to Chriſt his ſupreme King, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt his deputies and vicegerents. True undiſſembled Loyalty is the very complexion of a Chriſtian; and the beſt Chriſtians are always the moſt, I had almoſt ſaid the only Loyal Subjects. The Apoſtles therefore did not deny but inforce ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Magiſtrates. Indeed where the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God and their Prince interfer'd, in this caſe they reſolv'd to be faithful to God, and dar'd to do what he commanded, rho <hi>Ceſar</hi> forbid it. They did not deify their Emperor, but pay'd him all that reverence that was due to a Crowned Head. They accounted Princes Gods Subjects, and thought Rebellion againſt him a greater crime, than againſt the higheſt <hi>Monarch.</hi> In this caſe they appeal'd to their adverſaries themſelves whether<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 19.</note> reaſon was not on their ſide, couragiouſly ſaying, <hi>whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken to you rather than God, judge ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60423:32"/>But tho they could not actually obey the unjuſt Command of their Magiſtrates, yet then they made no violent reſiſtance, but paſſively ſubmitted to the exacted pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. As they profeſs'd a lowly Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Chriſt their King in Heaven, ſo they paid a reſpectful Obedience to his Lieutenants and Repreſentatives on Earth. They teſtifi'd their Loyalty to Chriſt, by the reſpect they gave to the Commands of his Deputies. Theſe <hi>Jews</hi> therefore had no reaſon to accuſe the Apoſtles, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragers of Rebellion; and in either of theſe ſenſes the Apoſtles were not blamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble turners of the World upſide down. They were wholly innocent in this latter ſenſe, and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſerv'd Commendation for diſturbing the World in the former ſenſe; and would to God the whole Chriſtian World at this day might be as eaſily defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Chriſt' and his Holy Apoſtles. And this leads me to the ſaddeſt part of my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>III. Queſt. <hi>Whether any profeſſed Chriſtians at this day, are guilty of turning the World upſide down?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A very little inquiry will preſent to our conſideration a potent Faction, that proudly Uſurps the name of the Catholick
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60423:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Church, whoſe Principles and Practiſes do clearly overturn the whole deſign of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and are pernicious to Governours; who have ſheltred Heatheniſh Superſtitions in Chriſtian Temples, after the Power of God had chas'd them away; and dug up ſome Limbs of the Ceremonial Law out of the Grave, after Divine Wiſdom had rung her Knell, and proclaim'd her Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. I know what an invidious task it is, to accuſe a whole Body of men; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, he that hath any Love to God, or his Redeemer, cannot account it a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful office, to ſatisfie his own Reaſon, or convince the Judgments of others, That his God is blaſphem'd, and his Saviour diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, by an huge party of men, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be of his Holy Religion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Infection is of a ſpreading nature, and the growth of Popery is too common, and too juſt a complaint; and the Bigots of that Church are continually uſing all the artifices of Cunning, and Inſinuation, and Treachery, to delude the eaſie multitude, and once more Introduce their blind Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into our Nation: I cannot think it an unſeaſonable work, but a piece of charity to the Souls of men, to give a juſt Character of that Religion, which if God had not, and did not ſtill mercifully interpoſe, would
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60423:33"/>
have again over ſpread this Land, as well as other Nations.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore purſue my former me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and inquire,</p>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>Whether they have introduc'd new Doctrines, different from what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught? and what warrant they can produce for doing ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that runs over the former parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, may ſoon be ſatisfi'd, that they have reſtor'd abſur'd Gentile Idolatry, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perannuated Jewiſh Ceremonies, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully corrupted Chriſtianity in thoſe great Articles wherein I have ſhow'd its pre-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to conſiſt.</p>
            <p>1. They have introduc'd new Doctrines concerning God, and the manner how he will be Worſhipp'd. This will be evident if we reflect upon theſe four particulars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their Repreſenting and Worſhipping God by Images.</item>
               <item>2. Their Adoration of Saints and Angels.</item>
               <item>3. Their Adoration of the Hoſt.</item>
               <item>4. The manner of their Worſhip too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſymbolizes with that of Jews and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. <hi>Their Repreſenting and Worſhipping God by Images.</hi> Thoſe who are acquainted with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60423:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any thing of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Worſhip, know how in their Churches, nay, in their Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Maſs-books, and Manuals of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the incomprehenſible Trinity is pictur'd: ſometimes like an old Man, with a long grey Beard, and a ray of light over his head, with a Crucifix between his Knees, or a Child in his Arms, and a Dove with ſpread Wings under his Beard. Sometimes like a Monſter, with three Faces in a Knot. Now, how abominably fooliſh and impious are ſuch Repreſentations as theſe? What ridiculous entertainment doth this afford to the <hi>Socinian?</hi> And how doth it expoſe this ſacred Myſtery, to his Deriſion and Contempt? How naturally doth this tend to debaſe the Divine Majeſty, as if the Infinite Lord of Angels and Men, bore any reſemblance to his imperfect Creatures; and the incomprehenſible Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, were like ſuch Worms and Duſt as we? If any man ſhould reverence a Worm, or a Toad, as the Image of his Prince, would not ſuch a mans honorary reſpect be interpreted as an high affront? And is it not an infinitely greater Indignity to Worſhip the Divine Majeſty in the ſhape of the moſt glorious of any of his Creatures? There is very great danger, leſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Vulgar ſhould fancy God like the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60423:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Images he is repreſented by; and they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tend at leaſt, to debaſe our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of his incomprehenſible nature. His Immenſity cannot be repreſented by a piece of Wood; nor his Infinity by a finite Idol. Images are apt to ſuggeſt too low Thoughts, and mean Apprehenſions of his Nature, and therefore are not to be us'd. If it be pleaded, That ſuch Repreſentations may be inſtrumental to raiſe our Thoughts, and excite dovout Affections within us. Alas! he that hath not rais'd Apprehenſions of the Divine Majeſty and Greatneſs, from the conſideration of his own glorious works, muſt expect little benefit by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Art and Invention of man. Let them therefore call Images Laymen's books; till they ſhow us Gods Licenſe and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur for them, we ſhall eſteem them as Surreptitious Pamphlets, offenſive to the King of Heaven. If it be again pleaded, That God (by his appearances to <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Patriarchs, in the form of a man, and his being repreſented as an old man to <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt's deſcent in the form of a Dove) hath authoriz'd ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations. I anſwer; The appearances to the Patriarchs were of the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity, as Anticipations of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and were no Repreſentations of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60423:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his Nature, but only ſigns that he was then, and there preſent. As to that in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 9. concerning the Ancient of days, that was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented to the inward ſenſe of <hi>Daniel</hi> in a Viſion, and was only a Symbol of Gods fitneſs to Judg the World: White, to denote the purity of his Nature; Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of days, to repreſent his eternity; and white hair, to ſhadow out his Wiſdom and Prudence. As to that of <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 16. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Expoſition takes off all neceſſity of anſwer, according to him, the Expreſſion (<hi>like a Dove</hi>) hath reference not to any aſſumed likeneſs,<note place="margin">Hammond <hi>in</hi> Matth. 3. 16.</note> but to the manner of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, that he came down upon him, as Doves uſe to do, when they light upon any thing, hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and overſhadowing it. Thus we know, the Holy Ghoſt deſcended on the Virgin <hi>Mary, Luke</hi> 1. 35. For St. <hi>Luke</hi> indeed adds, in a bodily ſhape; but that may be render'd with a bodily appearance; ſo that perhaps the Holy Ghoſt might appear in no outward Figure, but only appear to be preſent, by the appearance of Angels; and it is not unlikely it might be in a bright ſhining Cloud, as at the transfiguration of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17. 5. it is ſaid, <hi>A bright ſhining cloud overſhadow'd them,</hi> deſcending
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60423:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as Doves uſe to do. For the full confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this, I muſt refer to the place. But if the general Expoſition be allow'd, That the Holy Ghoſt did appear in ſuch a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Figure; this was only to repreſent the Innocence of our Saviour, and the purity and peaceableneſs of that Religion he was then beginning to teach the World: No repreſentation of his Nature. Nor can God be worſhipp'd under any corporal Figure, without palpable Idolatry. For, as ſoon may deliberate Murder and Adultery be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to the <hi>6th</hi> and <hi>7th,</hi> as this can to the <hi>2d.</hi> Commandment. And our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are very conſcious of this, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have very fairly expung'd it out of their Catechiſms and Manuals, and ſplit the tenth into two, to keep up the number. They had reaſon to fear, leſt the Laity not having ſuch Metaphyſical heads as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (if they had left it ſtanding) ſhould have been deterr'd from ſo gainful a ſin. For <hi>thou ſhalt not make a Graven Image,</hi> would quickly make their Temples deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; and, <hi>thou ſhalt not bow down to the likeneſs of any thing in Heaven or Earth,</hi> would open the eyes of their deluded Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, if they were but permitted to read them. Words ſo fully Emphatical and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, that all worſhip of Images could
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60423:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hardly have been condemn'd in more large and ſignificant terms. And <hi>Moſes,</hi> who beſt knew the meaning of the Lawgiver, hath given a clear comment upon this Command, Deut. 4. 15, 16. <hi>Take ye therefore good heed unto your ſelves, for you ſaw no manner of ſimilitude when the Lord appeared unto you in Horeb; leſt ye corrupt your ſelves, and worſhip Graven Images.</hi> If the Heathen Idolatry were only forbidden, of what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent arguing, would <hi>Moſes</hi> here be guilty? Take heed leſt ye worſhip the Images of falſe gods, for ye never ſaw any Repreſentation of the true God. But if all Worſhip of Images be here forbidden, then the Argument is very pertinent and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Take heed how ye Worſhip God in any outward Repreſentation; for if ſuch a thing were pleaſing to him, he would not have left it to your choice, to do it in what form you pleas'd, but would have appear'd in ſuch a likeneſs as beſt pleas'd himſelf.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the golden Calf, which the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> worſhipp'd as a reſemblance of God, was a breach of this Commandment, and is called an Idol, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 41. For that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did make this as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the true God, is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodus</hi> 32.</note> clear from the Story. <hi>Aaron</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60423:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſays, <hi>theſe be thy Gods,</hi> O Iſrael, <hi>that brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt; and Proclaims a Feaſt to <hi>Jehovah;</hi> for either we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to be ſo ſtupidly ſottiſh as to ſuppoſe this Calf to be really that God that brought them out of <hi>Egypt</hi> before it was made; or if we cannot find in our hearts to believe them ſo abſurd; we muſt believe they fell back to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or worſhipt the true God under this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation. That it was not a reſemblance of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Gods, is evident from hence, that he is call'd <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and is repreſented as the God that brought them out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for could they once imagine that the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Gods had deſtroy'd their own moſt zealous worſhippers, and wrought ſuch wonders for them who abhor'd their worſhip, and would give them no adoration? is it not much more rational to ſuppoſe, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> expected ſome ſymbol of the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence going before them? as they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound that promiſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 20. And (<hi>Moſes</hi> being<note place="margin">See more of this in <hi>Stillingſleets</hi> Defence of the Idolatry of <hi>R. C. Page 747</hi>
               </note> abſent for 40 Days) they doubting whether ever they ſhould ſee him more, deviſe with themſelves what token to have of Gods preſence with them; and the moſt part being ſway'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60423:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by their Education in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they worſhip'd their chief god <hi>Oſyris</hi> in the form of a Bull, compel <hi>Aaron</hi> to make a Golden Calf. And if this be in them accounted Idolatry, muſt not the ſame title be given to our <hi>Romiſh</hi> worſhippers of Graven Images? Of the ſame ſin was <hi>Micah</hi> guilty, in <hi>Judg.</hi> 17. who, to eaſe himſelf of the trouble of travelling ſo often to <hi>Sbiloh</hi> to worſhip there, made a molten and graven image as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Lord <hi>Jehovah;</hi> builds a Chappel in his houſe, and hires a <hi>Levite</hi> to be his Prieſt, and in this rejoyces exceedingly, <hi>now know I,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that the Lord will do me good, ſeeing I have a</hi> Levite <hi>to my Prieſt, Judg.</hi> 17. 13. Of the ſame nature was that great ſin of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> for which he is brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo black a Character in Scripture; he made two Calves in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> as a repreſentation of God. 'Tis plain he deſign'd not to draw the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, but from going up to Jeruſalem to Worſhip; leſt their converſe with the Two Loyal Tribes ſhould revive their principles of Loyalty alſo, and reduce them to their ſubjection to their Lawful Sovereign; and therefore his ſucceſſors were look'd upon as worſhippers of <hi>Jehovah.</hi> Thus <hi>Jehu</hi> was zealous for the Lord<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Jehovah,</hi> though he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60423:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not from this ſin of <hi>Jerobcam.</hi> Thus it appears, how plainly God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden all worſhip of him by images. And that this Law was not only poſitive and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, but unalter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly obliging all men, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the reaſon of the Law. The unſuitableneſs of an image to the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 18, 25. The Prophet rhere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſtately and majeſtick deſcription of the Divine Greatneſs, concludes with this infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; <hi>To whom then will ye liken God? Or what likeneſs will ye compare unto him?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Seeing God is ſo immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly Glorious a being, your own reaſons may convince you of the folly of making any repreſentations of him. John 4. 24. <hi>God is a Spirit, and will be worſhip'd in ſpirit and truth.</hi> That is, as ſome interpret the words, not in the Image of a Dove, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Worſhip'd him on Mount <hi>Gerizim;</hi> nor with the Typical Sliadows of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law. St. <hi>Paul</hi> when arguing with the <hi>Athenians,</hi> bends his diſcourſe againſt their Worſhipping the Sovereign God in the likeneſs of ſilyer, or gold, or ſtone, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 29. and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 23 He diſputes againſt the wiſer Philoſophers, and accuſes them, that when they knew God to be an Immenſly Glorious being, they faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd him like a man; and Worſhip'd him by Images; and the accuſation will equally
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60423:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
concern our preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> pretenders to Wiſdom. The ſame apologies the wiſe men of <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> made, to excuſe their Heatheniſh Idolatry, are adapted by the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Schools, to juſtify their worſhipping Images. <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and <hi>Celſus,</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> and <hi>Maximus Tyrius,</hi> and many others, tell us, they look'd upon Images only as helps to remembrance, and means of exciting their devotions; nay, the worſhippers of the Sun and Moon and Stars, might better apologize for themſelves; For theſe natural Images are great Monuments of the Divine Wiſdom, and Power, and Goodneſs; but the preſent artificial ones, expreſs only the Gravers skill and imperfect cunning. Nay further, the very ſame pleas might be us'd by the Prieſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to juſtify their moſt ridiculous follies. Leeks and Onions may as well draw forth my penitential tears; deified Apes and Monkeys may as well be the objects of my adoration, as the Monſtrous Pictures of the Trinity in their Temples. But how contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory ſoever this practiſe be to Scripture, Images may. well agree to that Church, which retains little more than the faine image and ſhadow of a Religion.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Their Adoration of Saints and Angels,</hi> and giving them the ſame Worſhip the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60423:38"/>
Heathens gave to their <hi>Daemons,</hi> or inferior <hi>Deities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Daemons,</hi> the Heathens underſtood an inferior ſort of deified powers, as middle Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings between the Sovereign God, and mortal men; and becauſe they thought the higher God too pure and ſublime to meddle with Earthly affairs, they placed theſe as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators to prefent the prayers of Men to God, and convey the benefits of God to Men; thus <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Heſiod,</hi> and others that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them. To this opinion the Apoſtle ſeems to allude, in 1 Cor. 8. 5. 6. <hi>As there be Gods many, and Lords many: yet to us there is but one God the Father, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, i. e.</hi> Tho the Heathens Worſhip'd many Supreme<note place="margin">See this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in <hi>Mede's</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of the later times.</note> Gods, and inferior powers, as Preſidents and Mediators in Earthly things; yet we Chriſtians acknowledg but one ſovereign Deity, and one Mediator, who preſents our Prayers to the Father, and brings us back the rewards of our Devotion from Heaven. Theſe the Heathens divided into two ſorts, ſuch as were too pure to inform a body, and ſuch as were the ſouls of deceaſed benefactors To theſe they erected Temples and Altars, made Images and Shrines, and gave them all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60423:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
expreſſions of Religious adoration The latter ſort were call'd <hi>Baaline,</hi> or <hi>Belim</hi> becauſe the firſt that was thus Canoniz'd was King <hi>Belus</hi> at <hi>Babilon,</hi> by <hi>Ninus</hi> his Son; and well may the Holy Ghoſt call that Church <hi>Babilon,</hi> which hath reviv'd that Idolatry which was firſt ſet up in that City. For is not the worſhip of Saints and Angels exactly parallel to this? Are not they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted into the ſame place, and the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices directed to them? Are not Temples dedicated to their honour? Images ſet up, and ſhrines conſecrated, before which their Votaries may pray unto them? Are not they worſhip'd with ſolemn invocations, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>outward ſigns of the loweſt reverence? How do the ignorant Vulgar proſtrate themſelves before their Statues? Waſh their feet with tears, and wipe them with their hair? And if the Image chance but to nod or ſmile, how do they go away rejoycing, as if they had met with their good Genius, or ſome Angel had ſaluted them from Heaven? I need not here tell what a number of Saints they have Canoniz'd, and how they have ſymboliz'd with the Heathen, in aſſigning them their particular offices; how they have Saints for every particular Nation and Country, Trade and Calling; for every ſtate and condition, for every diſeaſe of the body,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60423:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and all the accidents of humane life. I need not tell how they worſhip ſome who probably had never any other being than in their own imagination; How notoriouſly wicked perſons have been Canoniz'd; how Rebellion and Treaſon hath been accounted worthy an <hi>Apotheoſis;</hi> and very few have receiv'd that honour for their Religion and Loyalty. I need not tell what notorious blaſphemies are contain'd in their Prayers, eſpecially to the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> how ſhe is exalted to the Throne of God, and call'd the Mother of Grace, the Fountain of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Queen of Heaven, and the Mother of the Holy Trinity. How <hi>Bonaventure</hi> hath Printed the Pſalter of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, being nothing elſe but the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> wherein whatever is ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God or Chriſt, either by way of Prayer, or of Praiſe, is appli'd to her. Theſe things are publickly known, and cannot be contradicted.</p>
            <p>And we may well challenge the Heathen World, to preſent us with more daring uſurpations on the Divine Prerogative; the ſame arguments which prove the <hi>Pagans</hi> Idolaters for their worſhip of <hi>Daemons,</hi> will equally prove the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſuch, who have exactly written after their Copy, and tranſcrib'd (that I ſay not exceeded) their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60423:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
iniquities; the ſame pleas which <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Celus,</hi> and the other defenders of the Pagan Worſhip us'd, are made by theſe pretenders to Chriſtianity; and the ſame anſwers which <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Arnobius,</hi> and the other primitive Fathers gave, may be very well re torted by us upon them, as will appear to any one that will but conſult Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleet</hi> in his defence of the Idolatry of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. But to go no ſurther than Scripture; Did not our Saviour repel the Devils temptation with, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve?</hi> And ſhall a far leſs conſideration, than the Kingdoms of the Earth, prevail with us to fall down before Creatures, and pay them a Religious Adoration? How ſmartly doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> Argue againſt all Worſhipping of Angels, without any of thoſe diſtinctions which our Voluminous School-men have invented? Col. 2. 18. <hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward, in a voli n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary humility, and worſhipping of angels, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding into thoſe things which he hath not ſeen.</hi> It ſeems by his diſcourſe there were ſome Hereticks crept into the Church, who out of a pretence of their unworthineſs to make immediate addreſſes to the inviſible God, ſued to the Angels his Courtiers and Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites to plead their Cauſe. This Hereſy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60423:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a long time in <hi>Piſidia</hi> and <hi>Phrygia,</hi> where Oratories and Chappels were built to <hi>Michael,</hi> and the Angels, which was at laſt forbidden in one of the Canons of the Council of <hi>Laodicea.</hi> I know Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> hath a very witty and ſingular eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Text; That by the worſhip which was given by Angels, is meant the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law; and he Tranſlates the words, <hi>Let no man tempt you to become proſyeltes of the Jews.</hi> But why ſhould the Apoſtle uſe ſuch dark expreſſions, if this were the meaning? and what pretences of humility did they uſe, who perſwaded to comply with the Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> Or how did they intrude into things they had not ſeen? Whereas, if the words be underſtood properly, theſe words have a very good connexion; theſe Hereticks pretended humility to be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their worſhip; and were puffed up with a conceit of their knowledg of all the Orders and Offices of Angels; nor can we imagine they worſhip them as Supreme Gods, but only as Gods by participation, and Advocates with the Father, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> alſo calls them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is equally concern'd in this prohibition. Beſides, did not the Angel correct St. <hi>John,</hi> when out of a ſudden tranſport, he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to give him that reverence which bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60423:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
too near upon what the jealous God hath reſerv'd to himſelf: with a <hi>ſee thou do it not, I am thy fellow. Rev. 19. 10 ſervant; worſhip God;</hi> And ſhall we be fearleſs of the ſame Idolatry? The diſtinction of <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> will by no means ſalve the matter; for why could not the Angel have appli'd it as well as the Angelical Doctor can? Or why could not this inſpir'd Apoſtle have pleaded that he gave him only an inferior ſubordinate wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as well as the moſt illuminated School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</p>
            <p>'Tis of theſe Idolaters the Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak in 1 Tim. 4. 1, 2. <hi>Now the ſpirit ſaith expreſly,</hi> (perhaps in Dan. 11. 36, 37, 38.) <hi>That in the latter times ſome ſhall revolt from the faith.</hi> Revolt by Idolatry, which is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently call'd by that Title; <hi>Giving heed to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Spirits, i. e.</hi> attending to erroneous Doctrines, <hi>Doctrines of Divels or Daemons.</hi> Not of which they are the Authors, but the objects; Doctrines concerning <hi>Daemons, i. e.</hi> inferior Deities; <hi>Speaking lies in hypocriſy;</hi> or (as the Greek runs) <hi>through the hypocriſy of liars, i. e.</hi> Through the Deceit of Iying per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who ſhould ſeign miracles, and invent fabulous ſtories to ſupport this worſhip. The event hath ſo exactly anſwer'd the Apoſtles deſcription; <hi>Monks</hi> (the admirers of ſingle
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60423:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
life, being the firſt Authors of Saint-Worſhip, which they brought in by lying-Legends, and Fictitious Miracles; that if this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy doth not particularly concern them, they are very unhappy to come ſo near the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Their adoration of the Hoſt, upon pretence of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> This is another part of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Worſhip, not to be paralIell'd for abſurdity throughout the whole Gentile world; For to fancy that every ignorant Prieſt can with Five words ſpeaking; change a piece of Bread into God; and by virtue of ſuch a ſtrong fancy, to give it Divine Worſhip, is an inſtance of ſuch egregious folly, as expoſes Chriſtianity to the ſcorn of infidels, and hardens them in their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; a Doctrine that would make a Monſter of our bleſſed Redeemer, and give him 10000 bodies at once. A Doctrine, that ſubjects our Saviour to the will of every Prieſt, and daily renews his humiliation; A Doctrine, that makes the Covenant of Grace much more ſevere than the Law of Innocence, while it threatens damnation to all that will not disbelieve the agreeing ſences of the whole world of Animals; A Doctrine that deſtroys the very Foundations of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Converſe, and tends to the moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Scepticiſm imaginable. For if our
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60423:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Senſes are deceiv'd in ſo plain an inſtance, how know we but that we may be all very Phantaſms, and a bundle of Accidents with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſubſtance? A Doctrine, that hath a natural tendency to Infidelity, and is the ready road to the moſt damnable unbelief. For the miraculous Works of our Saviour, were the great convincing Evidences of the truth of Chriſtianity. <hi>What we have ſeen and heard</hi> (as one ſpeaks) was the Apoſtles Logick, and an appeal to Miracles, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Demonſtraion of the Spirit. So that if our Senſes deceive us in this inſtance, our Religion it ſelf may be falſe. The Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt, and all his wonderful Works, might, for ought we know, be Impoſtures and Deceits. Thus we ſee how naturally the Papiſt lends his Aſſiſtance to the Atheiſt and Unbeliever. A Doctrine, that calls God himſelf a Deceiver; for he plainly tells us, by the moſt certain kind of Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (to our Senſes) That here is bread; when if this be true, there is really none at all.</p>
            <p>In a word, A Doctrine ſo full of unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Contradictions, that had not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Council curs'd all deniers of it, I am perſwaded it would have long ago been renounc'd. A Doctrine contradictory to Senſe, inconſiſtent with Reaſon, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60423:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by expreſs words of Scripture. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly calls it Bread after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 15, 16. 11. 26, 27. A Doctrine bottom'd only upon one Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical Expreſſion. <hi>This is my Body;</hi> Which, how it can prove this prodigious Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, is not very eaſie to imagine; for did not Chriſts natural Body ſpeak this, while ſitting at the Table? And could his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples apprehend, they eat the ſame Body, or that the ſubſtance of the bread was vaniſh'd, and only the Accidents remaining? Did they ſo hardly believe his Reſurrection, and would they without one queſtion about it, digeſt this miracle far more amazing? Doth he not ſay, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me?</hi> And if the Popiſh Comment were true, would it be ſenſe, to ſay, <hi>Eat me in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me?</hi> Are not the terms Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical in one part of the Sacrament? <hi>This Cup is the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Teſtament in my Blood.</hi> And why ſhould this, rather than the other, be taken according to the literal meaning? Beſides, the ſame word is us'd concerning the Paſſover, to which the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds: And the <hi>Jews</hi> had no term more proper to expreſs (<hi>ſignifie</hi>) by, than this word (<hi>is) It is the Lords paſſover,</hi> Exod. 12. 11. <hi>i. e.</hi> a Memorial and Signification of the Lords paſſing over the houſes of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60423:42"/>
when he deſtroy'd the firſt-born of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and why ſhould not the ſame Senſe be given of this Sacrament of the new Covenant? It is a Memorial of that Body of Chriſt which was once Offer'd for our Sins. Thus we ſee, how unreaſonable the <hi>Roman</hi> Expoſition of this Text is; and yet they cannot pretend any clearer proof of this great abſurdity; but it is the great deſign of this Church, to conquer thoſe three miſchievous Enemies, <hi>Senſe, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Scripture;</hi> and when they have once done that, they may impoſe what they will upon thoſe reaſonable Beaſts their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Senſe,</hi> they continually repreſent as ſubject to many Illuſions, and unfit to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, in any weighty matters. <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they Tragically exclaim againſt, as a dangerous Weapon; and the mortifi'd Father <hi>Creſſy</hi> ſomewhere tells us, That it is the Wit and Judgment of Catholicks, to renounce their own Judgment, and depoſe their own Wit. <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſetting aſide the Authority of their Church, is of no more Validity with them, than <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables, or <hi>Mahomets Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran.</hi> And tho they pretend the unanimous conſent of the Fathers to their Doctrines; yet, becauſe the Teſtimonies of <hi>Irenaeus, Juſtin Martyr, Theodoret,</hi> Pope <hi>Galaſius,</hi> are ſo plain againſt them, they pretend,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60423:43"/>
that the Fathers being obſcure, the preſent Church muſt be the Judg of their meaning; but if we joyn iſſue here alſo, and agree to be judg'd by the majority of Votes in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, then they very charitably damn all the World but themſelves, and aſſume the proud title of <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Univerſal;</hi> ſo that the reſult of all is this; If we will not upon their bare Affirmation, ſwallow this heap of Contradictions, we muſt infallibly fall under the Council of <hi>Lateran's Anathema,</hi> and be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
            <p>But it is better to bear their curſes here, than by our ſinful compliance with their groſſeſt Idolatry, to endanger our Salvation for ever. For if there be no <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> of what tremendous Idolatry are they guilty, who pay Divine Honour to a piece of Bread, and give that Adoration to a Waſer-cake, which is due to God alone? who outdo the groſſeſt Idolatry of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and juſtifie the moſt ridiculous Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of the Infidel world? They only believ'd that ſome inviſible Deity, incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated it ſelf in the Creature they worſhipp'd, but never imagin'd that the whole ſubſtance was chang'd into God. A <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> more ſtrange, than the moſt poetical Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60423:43"/>
could ever contrive; nor can they ſave themſelves harmleſs, by pretending they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Bread to be God, and therefore if they err, it is the fault of their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not of their Wills: For when men will maintain ſuch an Error in ſpite of their own Senſe, and Reaſon, and Scripture, and the plain Doctrine of the Ancient Church, they are certainly guilty of not only material, but wilful formal Idolatry. But ſuppoſing this Doctrine ſometimes; yet ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies happens, that it is impoſſible to know whether this particular Bread be Tranſubſtantiated or not. For if the Prieſt have not a right Intention, and be not duly ordain'd, the Miracle will not follow; ſo that it is confeſſed by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that no man can have any other than a conjectural certainty, that he receives the Body of Chriſt, becauſe it depends upon the Prieſts intention, which no man can know. And now can it conſiſt with our duty (as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Taylors</hi> ſpeak) <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſſwaſ.</hi> page 149.</note> 
               <hi>to give Divine Worſhip to that thing, which we cannot certianly know to have a Divine Being?</hi> But further, if we ſhould ſuppoſe (by virtue of a ſtrong faith, ſuch as is able to ſwallow Mountains) that this miracle were always perform'd, yet will not this juſtifie our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60423:44"/>
For we are not bound externally to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<note place="margin">See this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument largely proſecuted in Funeral of the Maſs, <hi>Chap. 5.</hi>
               </note> God. wherever he is; but only where he diſplays ſome Beams of his Glory. Therefore our Saviour teacheth us to ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven;</hi> Why not in Earth, Air or Sea? God is in all theſe; but Heaven is the Throne of his Glory; and therefore, thither we are to direct our Eyes and Devotions. Upon this account, ſuppoſing Chriſts humanity really preſent, he is but as a Prince in diſguiſe, and hath none of his Robes of Majeſty, and therefore expects not our religious Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all that is adorable in Chriſt, is in the water of Baptiſm; there is his Godhead, Divine Perſon, and Attributes; and yet there we do not Worſhip him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not oblig'd to do it in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> ſuppoſing his Humanity really preſent. For if his Godhead (which is of it ſelf adorable) be not worſhipp'd, where there are no Beams of Glory; much leſs is his Manhood to be Worſhipp'd (which is not of it ſelf adorable) where there are no glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of it. Thoſe therefore, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Hoſt, at beſt, Worſhip God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a command; but are really groſſer
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60423:44"/>
Idolaters than the moſt Barbarous Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>The manner of the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Worſhip too exactly ſymbolizes with the ridiculous Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the</hi> Heathens, <hi>and forbidden Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the</hi> Jews; <hi>and is unſuitable to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature.</hi> The Heathens us'd many ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Ceremonies, and antick Rites, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Spells and Charms in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me</hi>-Papal hath equall'd, if not exceeded them in her fond Superſtitions. Here I might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell of their Chriſtening Bells, and touching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads, and charming Water, Salt and Spittle for caſting out Devils; their hallowing Medals, Swords, and <hi>Agnus Deis,</hi> for a ſecurity from temporal and ſpiritual Evils. Their ſtrange Actions in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſms and Conjurations; indeed their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Worſhip being in an unknown Language, looks like a Charm or Spell. I migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their muttering over little unintelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prayers, numbring them by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Beads; and vain Repetitions, too like the Tautologies of the Heathens, condemn'd by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. I might further inſtance in their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd Penances, ſome trifling and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, others ſevere and formidable. Their pilgrimages, walking barefoot, wearing Hair ſhirts, whipping and ſlaſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, like the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60423:45"/>
Worſhippers of the other Sanguinary Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Deities. In their ordinary Worſhip of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> the Prieſt turns himſelf five times about at the Alter, to denote the five Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſt; on the day of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, turns to the right hand, to ſignifie, that he hath a<note place="margin">Stopfords <hi>Parallel,</hi> page 261.</note> right Intention for himſelf and the people. He uſes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſtrange Bowings and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. Sometimes with his hands cloſe ſhut, and at other times ſpread abroad. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he cries aloud, and at other times mutters over ſome things to himſelf. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he makes as if he ſlept with his Eyes cloſe ſhut; then ſtarts up, and goes on with numerous mimical Actions, fitter for a Stage-play, than the Houſe of God. In the Sacrament of Baptiſm, the Child muſt be firſt blown upon, to drive away the Devil; Then hallow'd Salt is put in his Mouth, that he may be ſeaſon'd with Wiſdom. His Breaſt and Shoulders are anointed with holy Oyl, that he may be kept from evil Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and ſtrengthen'd to bear the Lords burden. His Mouth, Eyes, Ears, Noſtrils, Breaſt, and Forehead, are ſign'd with the ſign of the Croſs, that all may thereby be defended. A white Garment is put upon him, to betoken his Regeneration. A Veil on
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60423:45"/>
his head, in token that he is Crown'd with a Royal Diadem. A burning Wax-candle in his hand, to fulfil that ſaying of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men,</hi> &amp;c. And the Prieſts holy Spittle (for the very Excrements of ſuch a ſacred Perſon muſt needs be holy) muſt be ſtroak'd on his Ears and Noſtrils, that the one may be open'd to hear the word, and the other to diſcern between Good and Evil; and after all, follow the words of inſtitution. A bare Relation of theſe things is a ſufficient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation; and the conſideration of them, forc'd thoſe honeſt Expreſſions from <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Virgil, He that obſerves theſe things,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and is</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Invent.</hi> lib. 5. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>but modeſtly ſcrupulous, will ſay, He queſtions whether we imitate the Religion of the Ancient Heathens, or their Superſtitions.</hi> Theſe numerous my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Rites, are perfectly oppoſite to the Religion of our Saviour, and tend to bring in a dry Skelleton of bodily Actions, inſtead of the Spiritual Worſhip of the Goſpel. Nay, have they not gall'd the Necks of their Diſciples with that heavy Yoke of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies, which the Apoſtle would not impoſe on the Gentile Convers? Is not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perannuated Judaiſm reſtor'd, and the high Prieſt tranſlated from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Rome?</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:60423:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Are not their Pilgrimages and Jubilees, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamps at noon-day, and perfumes of Incenſe, diſtinction of Days, and Meats, and Rules about Faſting and Abſtinence, a perfect imitation of the <hi>Jews?</hi> Theſe hath the Infallible man at <hi>Rome</hi> reviv'd, as if he would correct the Divine Wiſdom that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd them; or at leaſt, as if the Church were now in its Dotage, and again were to be rul'd like a Child or Infant. But we have not ſo learn'd Chriſt. <hi>We are to remember, as Biſhop</hi> Taylor <hi>ſpeaks, That Figures and Shadows were for the</hi> Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>but light and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ductor Dub. <hi>lib. 3. c. 4. rul. 20. ſ. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for the New. The</hi> Egyptians <hi>did indeed teach Religion by Hierogliphical Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols; and the Schools of</hi> plato <hi>and</hi> Pythagoras, <hi>by Numbers and Figures; but we who walk in the light of the Goſpel, have an eaſier way of teaching the People; and are not to return to the Elements and Rituals of</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <hi>Schools. This manner of teaching by ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Actions is too low, too ſuſpicious, too Dangerous, to be mingled with Divine Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and unbefitting the gravity and ſpirituality of our Religion.</hi> Thus far he. Thus we ſee how they have overturn'd the firſt deſign of Chriſtianity. Obſcur'd the Light of the Goſpel, and inſtead of that compleat Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60423:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Nature of God, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Worſhip, laid down in Scripture, have by their Idolatry and Superſtition, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us unworthy Notions of his Attributes, and brought in that blindneſs and thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which was mercifully chas'd away by the Sunſhine of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>2. They have invaded Chriſts Mediato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Office. The Chriſtian Religion diſcovers the only means of reconciling ſinful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by the Incarnation, Death, and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lord Jeſus, who in purſuance of the great deſign of bringing us to Heaven; is inveſted with the Offices of King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his Church; all which the Papacy hath invaded.</p>
            <p>1. They have invaded Chriſts Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. By this, 'tis his Prerogative to give Laws to his Church, and Chriſtians are bound to pay him the Subjection and entire Obedience of their Hearts and Lives.</p>
            <p>If any therefore ſhall pretend a power of diſpenſing with his Laws, and untying their Obligation, of making new Articles of Faith, and condemning things plainly commanded by him. If any ſhall pretend without ſufficient Proof, a Vicarious delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Commiſſion from him, and uſurp the place of the Univerſal Law-giver of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60423:47"/>
World: Theſe muſt be acknowledg'd to be invaders of his Regal Office; and in how many Inſtances the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been thus bold, and Jaringly guilty, is too well known. How many new Articles have they obtruded on our belief, ſince the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of Scripture was ſealed? And how doth their Faith increaſe and decreaſe like the Moon? Tho the Apoſtle pronounces an <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt the higheſt pretended Saint or Angel, that ſhould Preach any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrine than what he had deliver'd to the <hi>Galatians, Gal.</hi> 1. 8. Yet the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>Trent,</hi> thoſe profeſſed Angels and Guardians of the Church, have levell d their curſes againſt all that will fear the threatnings of the Apoſtle, and will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their ſupplemental and corrupt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions with the ſame reverence and pious Affection that they do the Holy Scriptures. I need not tell how they have claim'd a power of diſſolving the Obligation of the moſt Solemn Oaths and Covenants, and of allowing Marriages in forbidden degrees. How they have made Fornication a leſſer Sin in a Clergy-men, than Marriage; tho the one be the Ordinance of God, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prohibited to any company of men; and the other forbidden by the very Law of Nature. I need not tell how the Pope
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60423:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath uſurp'd the Office of Univerſal Biſhop, and Vicar of Chriſt; tho Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reflected upon <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> for affecting ſuch a Titile, and call'd it the badg of Antichriſt. I need not tell how they have added five other Sacraments, to thoſe two inſtituted by our Saviour; what a number of Church-Officers they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, unknown in Scripture, and the pureſt Ages of the Church: Nor how they have Lorded it over the Conſciences of men, by rigorouſly impoſing numerous burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Ceremonies, which change the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Worſhip of the Goſpel, and alter its very Nature. 'Tis confeſs'd that Governours have a Power of impoſing indifferent things; and whatever tends to the more orderly and decent Adminiſtration of the Worſhip of God, may be the object of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. But when theſe are either vain and uſeleſs, or indecent in their number; when they are impos'd as parts of Worſhip, and neceſſary to Salvation: When they obſcure the Worſhip of God, and are more like the ſhadows of the Law, than becoming the light of the Goſpel; ſuch Impoſitions are Acts of Tyranny and Uſurpation. I ſhall conclude this head, with the mention of one more bold, tho acknowledg'd Invaſion of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60423:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Regal Office of Chriſt, and that is, their half Communions.</p>
            <p>They have ſnatcht away the Cup in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from the People, and ingroſs'd it to the Clergy. This was eſtabliſh'd as an Article of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, at the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and afterwads confirm'd at <hi>Trent.</hi> The chief remarkable Cauſes are theſe, <hi>Seeing that in divers parts of the World, there be ſome, who raſhly preſume to ſay, That Chriſtian People ought to receive the</hi> Euchariſt <hi>under both kinds; this preſent Holy General Council, being deſirous to provide for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the faithful, doth decree, That tho Jeſus Chriſt did Adminiſter the venerable Sacrament in both kinds, and tho in the primitive Church, the faithful did ſo receive it; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this cuſtom ought to be kept,</hi> i. e. <hi>that the Prieſt that ſays Maſs, ſhall communicate under both ſpecies of Bread and Wine, but the Lay people under that of Bread only<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and they that ſay the contrary, let them be expell'd as Hereticks, and grievouſly puniſh'd by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and his Officials.</hi> How horrible a Canon is this, and what a notorious Uſurpation of Chriſts Prerogative? They accuſe of Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Error, and Hereſie, all who dare (by their own Confeſſion) imitate Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the Primitive Church; for this only reaſon, ſome have been burnt at a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60423:48"/>
Stake, and it was an occaſion of cruel Wars and Bloodſhed in <hi>Germany.</hi> They indeed pretend this to be an indifferent circumſtance, to be continued, or remov'd at the Churches pleaſure. But why ſhould this be more indifferent than the Bread? Hath not Chriſt more expreſly commanded the drinking the one, than receiving the other? <hi>Drink ye all of it,</hi> ſays he, as if he foreſaw and deſign'd to prevent this great Corruption. And to argue, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> our Saviour tells us, Joh. 6. 53. <hi>Except ye drink the blood of the Son of man, ye have no life in you.</hi> Theſe words, if underſtood of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> pretend, prove the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Univerſal neceſſity of communicating under both kinds. So that, either this great prop of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> muſt be deſerted, or their half <hi>Communion</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd.</p>
            <p>2. They have invaded Chriſts Prieſtly Office. By this he hath fully ſatisfi'd Divine Juſtice, by giving himſelf a compleat Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for our Offences, and procur'd for us the pardon of Sin, the Graces of the Spirit, and eternal Happineſs, upon Condition of ſincere Obedience to his Laws; and now is enter'd into Heaven, and is by vertue of this Sacrifice our powerful Interceſſor at the Right hand of God. This Office alſo, is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60423:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhamefully invaded by thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; and that in theſe following in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>1. By their proud doctrine of Merit. Tho the Scriptures fully declare, that by grace we are ſaved, and eternal life is the free gift of God: tho our reaſons may convince us, that a Creature (how innocent ſoever) can deſerve nothing at his Creators hands; tho a little reflection upon our ſelves, will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many ſpots in our faireſt vertues, many blemiſhes in our beſt duties, many imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in our moſt religious exerciſe, many ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mixtures in our moſt unpolluted actions, and great defects in our beſt obedience: yet do theſe men boaſt of their good works, and account them not only ſpotleſs, but meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous too: but if all this zeal for good works (as one well obſerves) were deſigned to advance an holy life, the nobleneſs of the deſign might a little excuſe the fault: but alas! thoſe works which they moſt extol, are either pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of will-worſhip, that tend only to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Secular intereſt of their Church, as Pilgrimages, building Abbys, enriching Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, &amp;c. or elſe are ſuch actions as we think to be daring ſins; as murdering <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and perſons coldly affected to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Cauſe.</hi> Thus 'tis ſtoried concerning
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60423:49"/>
Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> that great Politician of <hi>France,</hi> that when he lay upon his death-bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Conſeſſor came to him to perform the laſt offices of charity, and urged him to a full confeſſion of all his ſins; the <hi>Cardinal</hi> mention'd only ſome little petty crimes, and told him thoſe were all he could recollect; at which the Confeſſor ſtarted, ſaying, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this ſickneſs hath rob'd your Grace of your memory: for we who have been plac'd in a lower ſphere, have obſerv'd many actions of a far deeper Dye: and then mention'd many Murders committed by his procurement. Oh (ſays the Cardinal) thoſe perſons were diſaffected to the Catholick Intereſt, and theſe are my good deeds with which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to preſent my Saviour. A ſtory that needs no other invective than the bare rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I would not willingly accuſe all, while ſome only are liable to this charge. For many <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors mean no more by merit, than that obligation God hath by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe laid upon himſelf, to reward our good works. And this I think none that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Nature of the Divine Promiſes can gainſay. Theſe men we accuſe only for the uſe of a proud improper term; tho once us'd by the ancient Fathers in an innocent ſence.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60423:50"/>
2. <hi>By their Doctrine of penance and Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi> Whereas the Scripture tells us, that Chriſt hath pai'd down a compleat Ranſom for our ſins, and it is through his Blood alone we can expect a freedom from the puniſhments we have deſerved; yet this Church hath Coind new diſtinctions between the temporary and eternal puniſhments of ſin; as if tho the latter be remov'd by the Blood of Chriſt, the former muſt be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi'd for by our ſelves either in this Life or in Purgatory. To this end they have given the Prieſts a commiſſion to injoyn penances for ſin as ſatisfactions to Divine Juſtice, and preventive of ſurther puniſhment. Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo Ludicrous and Trifling, that it is a ſign of great infatuation in any that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve by ſuch cheap and eaſy performances, to appeaſe the anger of an offended Deity. Penances conſiſting of little obſervances; ſuch as numbering their Prayers by their Beads, ſaying ſo many <hi>Avemaries</hi> at ſome priviledg'd Altars: in abſtaining from Fleſh for ſo many days, in whipping their bodies, in wearing hair-ſhirts, and the cords of the particular Orders, and numerous other little pieces of ſolly and ſuperſtition. By theſe means do they take off ſinners from their grateful love and duty to the Redeemer, and earneſt believing-applications to the Lord Jeſus,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60423:50"/>
who is appointed by the Father, as the ſole Mediator of his Church, and through whom alone we can expect deliverance from pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhments, whether temporal or eternal. Of the ſame nature is their Doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; a ſtate of torments in the other world, equal in degree, tho not in continuance to thoſe of Hell: wherein thoſe ſouls muſt ſry who have not ſatisfi'd for their ſins here, till their friends give money to the Prieſt to pray them thence. By this means the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Clergy are advanc'd, and the grandeur of that Church promoted. This hath enrich'd their Abbies, adorn'd their Chappels, fill'd their Coffers, and made good proviſion for all the begging Orders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. For while they ſcar'd the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with ſuch a terrible Doctrine, and yet pretended a power of Praying them thence; who would not give liberally to thoſe who were able to deliver them from ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of torment? A Doctrine which the honeſter of their Doctors acknowledg, is not to be found in cripture; and theſe who pretend to prove it thence, have brought ſuch lame and farfetch'd pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s as are as eaſily refuted as mention'd; the only Text that can with the leaſt probability be ſtretch'd to this ſenſe, is that of 1 Cor. 3. 15. <hi>He himſelf ſhall be ſav'd, yet ſo as by fire:</hi> But
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60423:51"/>
this is but a proverbical ſpeech, and by the context the meaning plainly appears to be, that he who holding the eſſentials of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity ſhall corrupt it by additions of other diſagreeing Doctrines, is in a very hazardous condition; and tho his ſalvation is poſſible, yet it is but as a mans, whoſe houſe is on fire about his ears, extreamly dubious and very uncertain; which how applicable to the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> hath been excellently ſhowed by others, and will further appear by this diſcourſe. But were there ſuch a place as this, what a derogation is it to the blood and prerogative of Chriſt, to think that money can procure a Releaſe from thence? The <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> I am ſure, tells us that <hi>they who truſt in their wealth, and boaſt themſelves in the multitude of their riches: none of them can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem his brother, or pay to God a Ranſom for him. Pſal.</hi> 49. 6. 7. But this is but Old-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament-Divinity, and Purgatory hath been built ſince that time; or rather the infallible Head of the Church will not be guided by the Laws of the Bible.</p>
            <p>For tho St. <hi>Peter</hi> would not ſell the gifts of the Spirit for Money, yet a fair purchaſe of eternal Life may be bought of his Succeſſor, if God would as willingly conſent as he. And we may invert St. <hi>Peters</hi> words, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 18. <hi>They
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60423:51"/>
are bought with corruptable things, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd by ſilver and gold,</hi> from the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry flames of Purgatory, tho not from that vain converſation receiv'd by tradition from their Fathers. But we have not ſo learn'd Chriſt. Scripture mentions but two places, <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> if we lead Pious and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lives, we may receive death with a joyful welcome, and need not allay our comforts by the fears of an after-reckoning in another world. And tho we may have been guilty of many venial ſins in a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, through infirmity, ſurpriſe, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den temptation, or of any more mortal ones of a deeper die; yet upon our ſincere repentance, the Blood of Chriſt, (without the fire of Purgatory) will cleanſe us from all theſe, and preſent us pure and ſpotleſs to the Father. But if we die in an impenitent ſtate, we ſhall be preſently doom'd to endleſs remedileſs torments, and all the wealth of the <hi>Indies</hi> will never procure us a deliverance thence: I might further mention their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſelling Indulgences for money, which happily occaſioned the reformation by <hi>Luther.</hi> By this they they have made eaſy compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſins, and the <hi>Taxa Cameroe Apoſtolicoe,</hi> a book publickly printed amongſt them, ſets down at what eaſy rates an abſolution may be obtained for the moſt unnatural vices.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60423:52"/>
Now what a direct tendency hath this to make men ſet light by their ſins, tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot the blood of the Son of God, and account the death and ſufferings of the Lord Jeſus perfectly unneceſſary?</p>
            <p>3. <hi>By their doctrine of the ſacrifice of the Maſs, as a formal expiation of the living and dead.</hi> Tho the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> makes the great excellence of Chriſts ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice above thoſe of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, to conſiſt in this, That it was ſo full and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, that it needs no repetition; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 12, 14. Yet the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have made it a great part of their Religion to offer him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day in the Maſs, as a propitiatory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſacrifice, and thus make his former ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice on the croſs incompleat and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or rather wholly unneceſſary; for Chriſt inſtituted the Sacrament before his paſſion; and if he then offer'd up himſelf as a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſins, what need was there at all of his bloody death and paſſion. It is acknowledged that the Euchariſt may be called a ſacrifice in the ſame improper ſenſe, as our prayers, and alms-deeds, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances are called ſo in Scripture; and if they will call it a commemorative ſacrifice, as it is a memorial of Chriſts once perfect offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up himſelf on the croſe; Or even a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory ſacrifice, as it is a means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiating
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60423:52"/>
the Divine favour, and ſeals and exhibits to us the real benefits purchaſed by his death; we need not quarrel about words if this be their only ſenſe And indeed as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> ſomewhere ſpeaks, take away Tranſubſtantiation, and the conceit of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and this wordy controverſy would quickly be ended.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>By their formal Invocation of Saints.</hi> The Scripture teaches us, that there is but one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus; and that none might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend there may be other Mediators of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, tho not of Redemption, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath prevented that diſtinction, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1.—4 compar'd; where the Apoſtle urges us to pray for all men, becauſe all of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Nation or Condition in the world are intereſted in Chriſts interceſſion. He is the only Mediator that prevailingly intercedes for us in Heaven. To make creatures the objects of our formal invocation, what is it but to make them competitors with Chriſt, and ſhare in his prerogative? We may as well aſcribe redemption to others, as inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Beſides, what a diſparagement is it to his Love that when he hath given us the largeſt aſſurances of his kindneſs, and ready acceptances of our prayers, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly promis'd that if we put our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60423:53"/>
in him, he will be our Advocate, and we ſhall have a gracious anſwer from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Nay when God the Father hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, that whatever we ask in the Name of the Lord Jeſus ſhall be granted: I ſay, how do we diſparage his love by begging others to plead our Cauſe? Can we imagine? that the ſervants of God can do more for us, than his beloved Son? Or the bleſſed Virgin, than the Lord Jeſus? He that looks into the <hi>Roman</hi> Rituals, indeed may be tempted to think ſo, where ten <hi>Avemaries</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd to one <hi>Paternoſter:</hi> and they have pictur'd Chriſt as frowning upon ſinners, and driving them away from him; but the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> inviting them with her ſmiles, and lending a willing ear to their Devotions. But he that looks into Scripture, there finds nothing of this nature. We are never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to put our confidence in man; but curſes denounc'd againſt thoſe that do ſo. The Saints in Heaven, are there never made the objects of our Prayers; and it was always thought by the Primitive Church, a good Argument againſt the <hi>Arriant,</hi> that Chriſt is God, becauſe we are directed to addreſs our ſelves to him Whether the Saints Pray for us or no in Heaven, is not the queſtion; and while we underſtand not the extent of their knowledg, it will remain a doubt, <hi>Luk.</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60423:53"/>
15. 7. Thoſe who rejoyce at the converſion of a ſinner, may perhaps as far as they know our condition, pray for their militant fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members: <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 9, 10. And thoſe who ſo paſſionately deſire that vengeance may be executed on the Churches enemies, may reaſonably be thought as earneſt for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their friends. But this their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion is not (as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> pretend) like the Lord Jeſus's, by preſenting their merits in our behalf; nor hath God given them power to pardon our ſins, heal our diſeaſes, ſupply our wants, or ſave our Souls; and yet for ſuch things as theſe, are prayers directed to them; nor is there any warrant from hence for us to make them our Mediators, and pray unto them. For tho they may know ſuch things concerning us, whereby their own happineſs and comfort may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd: yet that they ſhould underſtand all the particular grievances and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our lives, hear our prayers, or know our hearts, is not to be imagin'd. And when we uſe the ſame geſtures of external adoration to them, that we do to our Saviour, we thereby make them copartners with him in the ſame honour, and rivals to him in his dignity.</p>
            <p>3. They have invaded Chriſts Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal office. By this, he hath reveal'd the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60423:54"/>
whole will of God unto us: and that we might not be deceiv'd by the ſubtilties of ſeducers, Commiſſion'd his inſpir'd Apoſtles to commit his precepts to writing in the Holy Scripture, that this might be our ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rule. According to this we are bound to walk; and whatever Doctrines or practices are not agreeable to it, muſt be diſown'd. This Office is alſo invaded by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and moſt eminently by theſe following ways.</p>
            <p>1. By hiding the Scripture from the common people, and to juſtify this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, accuſing it of obſcurity. 'Tis well known how they have forbid the Scriptures to be Read in the vulgar language, and by terrible curſes and Anathema's have ſcar'd their Lay-proſelytes from this admirable guide to happineſs. How have they lock'd up this bread of life, and ingroſs'd this facred Manna to themſelves! How have they inclos'd this well of Salvation, and churliſhly refus'd their Laity ſo much as a taſt of the purer ſtreams, except they will take in the mud and filth, and their own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure mixtures alſo. Their people muſt be content with the crumbs which the Clergy are pleas'd to let fall: and be ſatisfi'd with only a glimmering of that light which would
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60423:54"/>
clearly direct them to the paths of Life. The Scriptures, like the riſing Sun, would quickly diſpel the darkneſs of error, and their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ignorance: and therefore the proud Prelates reſolve to ſtop this Giant in his race, and hinder him from ſcattering his Beams in the World: But alas, what an high af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front and daring in dignity is this, to the great Prophet of the Church? That when he deſcended from his Fathers Boſom for this very end, that he might diſcover the mind and will of God unto us; took ſuch unwearied pains to publiſh his Doctrine; ſtrengthend it by ſuch amazing Miracles; and inſpired his Apoſtles, that they might commit to writing this his laſt Teſtament and admirable Legacy: I ſay, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous piece of Ingratitude is it, to hide it from the ſight of thoſe to whom it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd by our Lord? And that by them who pretend to be the Guardians of it, and the Executors of their departed Saviour? Such an Action might be more excuſable in <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> or <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> but for the Vicar of Chriſt to be Guilty of it, is a crime ſufficient to forfeit his Title, and tempts us to believe him Antichriſt. Was the Scripture firſt Preach'd, and afterwards written in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage capable of being Univerſally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood? And is there not as much neceſſity
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60423:55"/>
it ſhould be ſo continued? Did God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Jews</hi> to be frequent in the Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law? To lodg it in their thoughts, to make it their daily companion, and the ſubject of their conſtant entertainment? And hath<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. 18, 19, 20.</note> he any where forbidden the uſe of the Goſpel? To delight in the Law of the Lord, and to Meditate therein day and night, was once the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 1, 2.</note> of a Bleſſed Man. And is the ſcene ſo much chang'd, that now it is become the black mark of a damnable Heretick? The Prophets permitted the People to judg by the Scriptures, which were true, and which were counterfeit meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers from Heaven, crying out, <hi>to the Law, and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, 'tis becauſe there is no</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20.</note> 
               <hi>light in them!</hi> And muſt we acknowledg theſe men for the Pillars of Truth, and the Lights of the World, without being allow'd the ſame liberty? When our Saviour was ask'd by that young man, <hi>what ſhall I do that I may inherit eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life?</hi> Our Lord anſwers him; <hi>what ſaith the Law? How Readeſt thou?</hi> And ſhall ignorance be now accounted the ſureſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60423:55"/>
Road to Heaven? <hi>Search the Scripture,</hi> was his precept, but is the prohibition of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church. <hi>Timothy</hi> and the <hi>Bereans</hi> were indeed commended by St. <hi>Luke</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as noble perſons for their diligence in the Scriptures: But if they had liv'd in the days of our Modern Saints, this would have been thought a crime deſerving the laſh of the inquiſition. An <hi>Anathema</hi> would have been their ſpiritual reward, and fire and faggot their civil recompence. Certainly ſuch a practice as this, had need be back'd with good Apologies, or elſe they will never be able to juſtify ſo great an abuſe of the Lord Jeſus. But how weak are their pleas! and how inſignificant the excuſes they make! Is it becauſe the People may wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to their perdition, that they are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their uſe? Alas! becauſe ſome may abuſe it, muſt all therefore be depriv'd of it? becauſe ſome may make Scripture the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their errors, muſt it not therefore be the foundation of truth? Becauſe ſome dogs have trampled on the Bread of Life, Muſt the Children therefore be withheld from their Spiritual Food? Becauſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks have taken too large draughts of the new Wine of the Goſpel, muſt all therefore be denied to taſt of it? Becauſe ſome know not the worth of theſe Pearls, muſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60423:56"/>
thoſe therefore who know how to value them, be hinder'd from their poſſeſſion? By the ſame reaſon the Scriptures ſhould not be permitted in the Learned Languages; for Learned Men have been generally the firſt broachers of Hereſy, and are moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of perverting the Holy Writings. Is it becauſe Scripture is ſo obſcure, that if the common people did injoy it, they could not underſtand it? 'Tis acknowledged, there are myſteries in our Religion, and God hath for wiſe ends left ſome things more dark and obſcure, to awaken our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, abate our Pride, and ſhow the moſt Learned, his ignorance and infancy in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; and create in us all, earneſt longings after that Happy ſtate, where all the Riddles ſhall be unfolded, and the myſteries clearly reveal'd. But there is ſo much perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly laid down, as is neceſſary to Salvation; and every man that Reads it, and ſincerely endeavours to underſtand it, ſhall with the help of Divine Grace, arrive at ſo much Knowledg, as if improv'd into practice, will bring him to Heaven. The great end why the Scripture was written, was, that we might have a conſtant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor of our duty, and guide<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> to happineſs; now if the Scripture were ſo obſcure that it anſwer'd
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60423:56"/>
not this end, this would reflect upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom, as if he had choſen an inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient means, and were defeated in his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and expectations. And it would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually reflect upon his goodneſs, as if he envied his creatures happineſs, if after our ſincere and humble endeavours, we could not underſtand the things that are neceſſary to our Salvation. The eſſentials are clearly reveal'd; tho there be ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure paſſages, yet the Divine Goodneſs hath left them, not that we ſhould be debar'd from Reading, but to prevent our loathing and contempt: and the darkeſt phraſes are incomparably more intelligible than the cloudy obſcurities of their admired Authors. The pious nonſence of Mother <hi>Juliana,</hi> and the ſanctifi'd gibberiſh of their myſtical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, are infinitely leſs perſpicuous than the Prophecies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> or myſteries of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> And yet thoſe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on Chriſtianity, as if it conſiſted only in <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> heats and raprures, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, while the Scripture which gives ſo lovely a deſcription of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be ſhut up from the ſight of the multitude. But whatever ſlender pretences may be us'd to delude perverſe Hereticks, we have good ground to think, that the true cauſe of this Reſtraint, is the ſame which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60423:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our Saviour mentions, Joh. 3. 19. <hi>They love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evil.</hi> Should the Scriptures be read by all, their Proſelytes would be few, and their Altars would no longer ſmoke; the Grandeur of the Church muſt be abated, the infallible Chair would totter, and <hi>Rome</hi> would be no longér the Miſtreſs of the Earth.</p>
            <p>2. Their pretence of Infallibility, and the Scriptures dependance on the Authority of their Church. This is another Invaſion on Chriſts Prophetical Office. For if Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be lodg'd in either Pope or Council (for they are not agreed where it is plac'd) then tho Chriſt hath never ſo clearly explain'd his mind, they may make what Expoſitions of his words they pleaſe, and obtrude them on our belief. Their great Champion <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſerts, That if the infallible Head ſhould condemn Vertue for Vice, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Vice as Vertue; we are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Vice as morally good, and Virtue evil, but if this be Goſpel, our great Maſter hath deceiv'd us, and we have been led by our Saviour into an Error. Then if that impure Cardinal, that writ a Book in praiſe of the ſcarlet Sin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> had been exalted to the Papal-chair, and from thence proclaim'd that unnatural Vice to be morally good, we
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60423:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhould have been bound to believe it. And tho ſome pretend that ſuch a Suppoſition is not to be made, becauſe the Spirit of truth will guide the unerring Head into all truth; yet, ſad experience hath taught us, that the broadeſt Impieties have been canonized, and miſcal'd Virtue and Juſtice at <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides, what poſſible reaſon is there, they ſhould be ſecur'd from Error more than from Sin? How can it be imagin'd that that Holy Spirit, which is griev'd with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and will not dwell in the Habitations of uncleanneſs, did infallibly aſſiſt thoſe Monſters for Villany, which are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Platina</hi> to have worn the Triple Crown in the ninth and tenth Centuries?</p>
            <p>Surely if ſuch a gift as this was ever given to the Guides of the Church; How obſcure ſoever the Scripture be in other things, it will be highly neceſſary it ſhould plainly lay down this important Doctrine. But alas! How impertinent are the Proofs they bring! They are either ſuch as will equally prove the Civil Magiſtrates, and Judges in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall</hi> infallible: Such is that, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 10, 11, 12. Where Judges are appointed to decide matters of Difference between man and man, to whoſe Deciſions the People are bound to agree, that their Strifes might not
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60423:58"/>
be endleſs, or ſuch as are reſtrain'd to the Apoſtles themſelves. Such is that, <hi>Mat. 16. 19. I will give thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatſoever thou bindeſt on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven; and whatſoever thou looſeſt on earth, ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> The plain meaning of which words ſeems to be only this. I will give thee the the priviledg of firſt opening<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> in locum.</note> the Goſpel (frequently call'd the Kingdom of Heaven) and whatſoever parts of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law thou bindeſt to the Obſervation of, or takeſt off the Obligation, (for ſo the Phraſes of binding and looſing are generally us'd in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers) ſhall be obſerv'd and forborn. God will ratifie and confirm what thou eſtabliſheſt. Accordingly we know St. <hi>Peter</hi> did firſt Preach the Goſpel to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and to the <hi>Gentiles, Acts</hi> 10. And this priviledg of binding and looſing was peculiar to him and the other Apoſtles. Laſtly, Their proofs are ſuch as agree to every particular Church, and faithful Chriſtian. Thus that of <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. 17. Speaks only of a Juriſdiction in every Church for quieting differences among the Members of it. And that other of Matt. 16. 18. <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church.</hi> For by the Gates of Hell may
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60423:58"/>
be either underſtood the crafts and policies of Hell (Councils uſing to ſit in the Gates of Cities) ſhall not totally prevail; There ſhall be a body of Chriſtians in the World, or the Tranſlation ſhould be mended, and the words read (the Gates of the Grave, or the inviſible State) Death, which is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently call'd among the <hi>Greeks</hi> by that name, ſhall not gain Victory over the Church, over the particular Perſons of which it conſiſts; tho they dye, yet Chriſt will reſcue them by a glorious Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Death ſhall not have Dominion over them, nor over the Church; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its many Enemies; it ſhall not periſh totally or irrecoverably. Theſe are the beſt proofs of their Infallibility, I can find in the Scripture; and while they are ſo eaſily and naturally applicable to a different ſenſe, I cannot think a Doctrine ſo obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliver'd in the Chriſtian Rule, to be any Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. Beſides, what uſe do they make of this gift they pretend to? Have they oblig'd the World by an infallible Comment on all the difficult places in Scripture, and put a final end to all controverſies among themſelves? On the contrary, have not ſome Popes profeſs'd their no skill in Divinity, and infallible Councils contradicted each other? Are not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60423:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there violent diſputes between the <hi>Franſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> and <hi>Dominicans, Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits, French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Clergy? Surely the Pope muſt be very regardleſs of the Peace of the Church, who will not give an infallible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the truth. And if ever God did give this gift, ſince the Apoſtles days, he may have long ſince juſtly taken it away, becauſe they have hid their Talent, and made no uſe of it. And now I have weaken'd this pretence, the other of the Scriptures dependance on the Authority of their Church falls of it ſelf; for if their Church be not infallible, why ſhould I believe the Scriptures to be Gods Word, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſay ſo, any more than <hi>Mahomets Alchoran?</hi> 'Tis true, the Teſtimony of their Church, jointly with all other Chriſtians in the World, and the Confeſſion of <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathens, handed down to us by the moſt unqueſtionable hiſtorical Tradition, is a great Confirmation, that theſe were the Books indicted by the Apoſtles, that they were confirm'd by various Miracles, and are not corrupted in any material Articles; but we believe their Divine Authority, not becauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Church ſays ſo, but becauſe of thoſe Seals which God hath affix'd to them. We have convincing Arguments enough, of the Scriptures Divinity, and need not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60423:59"/>
go to <hi>Rome,</hi> to know what they mean Chriſt hath fully prov'd, that his Meſſage is from God, by the excellence of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, the accompliſhment of Prophecies, and numerous miraculous Works; and we will not forſake theſe firm foundations of our Faith, and be ſo unreaſonably credulous, as to believe the ſame things meerly upon the Affirmation of a company of the worſt ſorts of Chriſtians in the World. Thus have they dangerouſly invaded the Offices of Chriſt. I proceed to</p>
            <p>3. They have corrupted the excellent Rules of an holy Life contain'd in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. The great deſign of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is, to purifie and amend the World, and reduce it to its primitive Innocence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And I wiſh there were leſs occaſion to think, that the deſign of theſe men is to Debauch the World, and ſhow that it is poſſible to be more corrupt than the very Heathens themſelves; for have not they by their nice diſtictions, render'd a holy Life a very needleſs thing, and overturn'd the very foundations of Virtue and Morality? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that firſt Introduction to an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life, conſiſting in ſuch a hearty Sorrow for every Sin, as influences the practice, and diſpoſes us to forſake them, they have made utterly unneceſſary. For while they
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60423:60"/>
diſtinguiſh Sins into Mortal and Venial, and impoſe very eaſie Penances for thoſe of the moſt purple dye: Is not this the way to tempt their Proſelytes to a continuance in their Sins, and keep them from that ſevere hatred of them, and thoſe firm Reſolutions of forſaking them, they ought to take up? Beſides, they maintain that a ſlight Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and imperfect Sorrow for Sin, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the conſideration of ſome tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral inconvenience, if join'd with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Penance, is ſufficient to fit a man for Heaven, ſo that it is a very needleſs thing to hate or forſake our evil ways; This is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin'd by their Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintain'd by their moſt famous <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi> And <hi>Morinus</hi> tells us, as I find him quoted by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Preface to Anſwer to ſeveral Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes.</note> 
               <hi>That the excellence of the Evangelical Precepts above the Legal, chiefly conſiſts in this, That by them we are freed from the heavy yoke of Contrition and Love to God. A Speech that would better become a</hi> Turk <hi>or Heathen, than a Chriſtian.</hi> Thus we ſee they have hinder'd the firſt entrance into an holy Life, and made the Gate to Heaven wider, and the paſſage much more eaſie than our Saviour or his Apoſtles. And if we run over all the parts of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60423:60"/>
our Duty, we may find too plain a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction among their <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi> If we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Duties of Piety towards God; How neceſſarily muſt they have low and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverent thoughts of his imcomprehenſible Majeſty, who behold ſuch ſcandalous Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of him in their Churches, and ſee the ſame Devotions and Geſtures of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration us'd to thoſe who were once, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, equally ſinful Creatures with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? How have they incourag'd an abuſe of his ſacred Name, by their Doctrine of Equivocation; and prophan'd his Holy Day, by allowing the remains of that time, that is not ſpent at Maſs, to be imploy'd in idle Sports, and fooliſh Mirth? How have they deſtroy'd that truſt we ought to place on God alone, by teaching men to rely on Creatures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>; and damp'd well-grounded hopes of Heaven, by unreaſonable fears of Purgatory? How have they taken off all neceſſity of Faith in Chriſt, by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of implicite Faith; and while they teach the ſalvability of Heathens, will not allow that any Chriſtian can be ſav'd, who is not a Subject to the Pope? and thus a belief in him, is more neceſſary than in the Lord Jeſus. I might give many inſtances out of their <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> how they make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary to love God above once a year;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60423:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and if they ſay their Prayers, no matter whether they attend to them or no. The Duties of Juſtice and common Honeſty, are as perfectly overthrown by the nice Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of <hi>Rome.</hi> Their maintaining it lawful to exerciſe Revenge, and Kill him that hath injur'd us in Honour, Goods, or Reputation, is certainly no way own'd by our Saviour, who commands us to love our Enemies, and do good to them that hate us; by no means to avenge our ſelves, but to <hi>overcome evil with good.</hi> That La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of uncleanneſs, and immodeſty al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd in their Books, is but a very bad Comment upon that Text. <hi>He that looks upon a Woman, to Luſt after her, hath committed Adultry already with her in his heart.</hi> Neither were they ever incourag'd by him, who ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not for ſwear thy ſelf,</hi> to falſifie their Oaths, or violate their Faith with Hereticks. The great pattern of meekneſs and compaſſion, that check'd his Diſciples fiery zeal againſt the <hi>Samaritans</hi> with, <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of;</hi> Never encourag'd their envenom'd rage againſt Diſſenters from them; Never encourag'd their Gibbets, Stakes, or Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Nor did he command that all ſhould be tortur'd with the moſt bloody<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cruelty, who are ſo obſtinately ſullen, as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60423:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to refuſe to ſtoop to a Wafer-Cake, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their own ſenſes before his Holineſs. They have turn'd Nupitals into Maſſacres, and at the concluſion of Wedding-Feaſts have not tranſubſtantiated, but exchang'd Wine for Blood. They have treacherouſly murder'd thouſands of Innocents, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly ſung praiſes to God, as if he were the Author of thoſe Villanies which are highly-diſpleaſing to him, and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly odious in his ſight.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel teaches us to maintain the moſt diffuſive unbounded Charity towards all the world; but they have conſin'd their love within the Walls of <hi>Rome.</hi> And like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, will allow no Salvation to any other Chriſtians, that will not ſubmit to the uſurpations of their High-Prieſt and Sanhedrim. The Chriſtian Religion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to abate our pride, and cure our ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs: But the great deſign of theſe men, is to aggrandize their Church, and promote the Secular intereſts of the Clergy. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-mindedneſs and ſelf-denial is every where urg'd in the Goſpel: But that the great corruptions for which we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do plainly aim at a worldly intereſt, may eaſily appear by an induction of the particulars I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60423:62"/>
diſcours'd of. And tho there are many Cloyſter'd Votaries among them, that make great boaſts of their mortification, who pretend to bid adien to the world, and all its flattering vanities, who pretend to ſpend their whole time in devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and dreſſing their Souls for Heaven: yet all this may be a juggle and cheat to blind the world; Phariſaical, and not Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical. And if we might be allow'd to ſearch their Cells and Abbeys, we might perhaps find they have been more careful to lay up Treaſures on Earth, than Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true Mortification is chiefly inward, but theirs is moſtly in externals. Their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion lies no deeper than their skins; and tho the Apoſtle tells us, that this bodily exerciſe profiteth little; yet they make it the very ſum of their ſelf-denial. Thus have they Evacuated the great duties of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And tho I cannot ſay that all theſe are Doctrines defin'd by their Councils, and in that ſenſe to be ſubſcrib'd to by all that Communion; Yet they are publickly Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Caſuiſts; and the order of Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, who moſt propagate them, are moſt encourag'd. And while a denier of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation ſhall be Sacrific'd to the Flames, theſe debauchers of the World, enjoy the beſt Eccleſiaſtical Promotions. I
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60423:62"/>
might have enlarg'd in further inſtances; but he that deſires more, may read enough to turn his ſtomach in <hi>Taylors</hi> Diſſwaſive from Popery, the Practical Divinity of the Papiſts; to omit the Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm, and the Jeſuits Morals. He that Reads thoſe collections out of their own Authors, will find, that the Pious and Judicious Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> did not go beyond the bounds of his wonted moderation, when he us'd theſe ſeemingly harſh expreſſions</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Sermon on 5th <hi>Nov. -78.</hi>
                  </note> I ſpeak it with grief (ſays he) and ſhame, becauſe the credit of our common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is ſome way concern'd in it; That <hi>Panaetius,</hi> and <hi>Antipater,</hi> and <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Stoick; Tully,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> were much honeſter and more Chriſtian Caſuiſts than the Jeſuits, or the generality of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts of any other Order that I know of in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I appli'd the firſt ſenſe of theſe words to theſe men: and I think ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved, That they have overturned the whole deſign of the Goſpel. I proceed therefore to inquire, Whether they can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any divine commiſſion for theſe great alterations they have made. Are their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines reaſonable? or have they any intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60423:63"/>
excellence to commend them? The Doctrines of the Apoſtles were highly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and their worth and excellence at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted every unprejudic'd perſon. But theirs are plainly abſur'd and irrational; ſuch as none but the wilfully blind and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly obſtinate can believe. For is it reaſonable to worſhip the incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God, by Images of Wood and Stone? and to give the ſame veneration to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that we do to the Lord of Angels and Men? Is it reaſonable to adore a Wafer-cake, or imagine that the charming words of a Prieſt, can fetch down the Body of Chriſt from Heaven, and convey away the Bread in an inſtant? Is it reaſonable to believe, that Chriſts Body may be in a thouſand places at once? that it may be divided, not into parts, but wholes, and crowded into every crumb of the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Wafer? Is it reaſonable to believe theſe and a 1000 more fulſome contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which that hard word <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> implies? Is it reaſonable to worſhip a ſpiritual Being, with gay ceremonies, and all the little pieces of ſoppery us'd in their worſhip? Is it reaſonable to believe, that God ſhould be ſo fond of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> that the Biſhop thereof, tho never ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60423:63"/>
for ignorance and villany, ſhall become infallible? Is it reaſonable to believe, that Abſolution can change Attrition into effectual Repentance, and the Omnipotent Words of a Prieſt conjure a man to Heaven in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant? But the world knows how the Jeſuit <hi>Veronius</hi> hath implicitely confeſs'd Reaſon not to be on their ſide, who preſented the world with a new method more promiſing than ordinary to convince Hereticks, and that was, to call for expreſs words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and abſolutely deny whatever reaſon ſaid againſt any of the Articles of their new Belief. And now ſince their Doctrines are thus confeſſedly unreaſonable, we may be aſſur'd they came not from Heaven, or the God of Reaſon.</p>
            <p>2. Are their Doctrines warranted by any Prophecies concerning them? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles compleated thoſe Prophecies that had been long before made. God had foretold his aboliſhing the Ceremonial Law, and eſtabliſhing a perfect ſtanding-rule for <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> But doth he any where fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, That after the expiration of ſo many Years, <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm</hi> ſhould be mix'd together by his appointment? On the contrary, the Goſpel is call'd an everlaſting
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60423:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Goſpel; and at the cloſing of the Canon of Scripture, a<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 18.</note> terrible curſe is denounc'd againſt thoſe who ſhould dare to make any additions to Scripture. There are ſome Prophecies indeed in Scripture, which ſeem to concern them. St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> have ſpoken many things concerning Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and the Man of Sin, which many think are clearly applicable to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But I know ſhe will ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe, as <hi>Ahab</hi> of <hi>Micaiah; I hate theſe men, for they Prophecy not good, but evil concerning me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Can they atteſt the truth of their Doctrine by Miracles? Here I know they will make their boaſts? There is not a Saint among them, but is famous for incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible wonders. The Apoſtles were but puny Miracle-workers, in compariſon of their Modern Saints. And the great St. <hi>Francis,</hi> St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> St. <hi>Catharine,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> far exceeded St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or St. <hi>James,</hi> or St. <hi>John,</hi> or any of the other Diſciples. Who can queſtion the lawfulneſs of Worſhipping the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> when he hears, that the Angels brought wood and ſtone croſs the Sea to <hi>Loretto,</hi> and built her
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60423:64"/>
a Chappel there? Who can forbear falling proſtrate, and crying, St. <hi>Thomas</hi> help me, when thoſe very words from the mouth of a Sparrow, ſtruck a cruel Sparrow hawk dead, that had almoſt faſtned upon her as his prey? Have not the wild beaſts of the wood fallen down before the Hoſt, when caſually let fall, and the very Aſſes caſt themſelves into a worſhipping poſture? And is it not mighty ſtrange, that men will ſtill truſt their own ſenſes, and remain Hereticks after ſuch wonderful evidence? I might inſtance in manyother pretty tales out of their Legends; but they are ſo ridiculous and extravagant, as plainly ſpeak out their forgery: and the wiſer among them are forc'd to confeſs them Pious Frauds, and Godly Cheats. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and his Apoſtles did their mighty works openly in the ſight of their greateſt enemies. But theſe are all tranſacted in corners, before friends, and thoſe that have already entertain'd their doctrines. And ſurely there muſt be ſome <hi>Legerdemain</hi> in the buſineſs, that ſo many Miracles ſhould be done in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and none in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> But the true reaſon why they can do no mighty works in our Country, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our unbelief. Proteſtants would ſoon diſcover their cheats; and they were
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60423:65"/>
once ſo baffled in that intended miracle of the Boy of <hi>Bilſon</hi> (a known ſtory) that they have hardly ventur'd the expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſince. Their Miracles, when they are not plain forgeries, are either the curing of melancholly ſumes, or Hyſterical-Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which frequently create fancies in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as if they were poſſeſs'd: of which inſtances have been given by Proteſtants (particularly, as I remember, by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) who have cur'd ſuch, and might have gain'd the name of Miracle-workers as well as they. Or if any of their <hi>Indian</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as <hi>Xavier,</hi> and had a true miraculous power, it was to confirm the truth of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to the Heathens; and not their addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional corruptions. Finally, if God do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to do ſome ſtrange unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table actions, to confirm their errors, 'tis but as a trial to our faith, to ſee whether we will forſake the true Doctrine confirm'd by greater miracles, when we are fore-arm'd againſt ſuch aſlaults, by being told, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhall come with lying wonders: and we need not fear the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, if we ſay, that by <hi>Beelzebub</hi> do theſe men caſt out Devils. But I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got one great Miracle, which is daily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd: and that is Tranſubſtantiation;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60423:65"/>
But thoſe who believe this, muſt live by faith, or rather unreaſonable credulity, and not by ſight. And the greateſt Miracle of all is, That men who are Wiſe and Rational enough in common matters, ſhould ſwallow ſuch an heap of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions. And thus have I made good the Charge againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church in the firſt Senſe; and tho much more might have been ſaid; yet this fully proves that they have corrupted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity with their impure mixtures, and cover'd the excellent Foundations of our Faith, with the Hay and Stubble of their own Inventions. And thus I proceed to make good the Charge againſt them in the ſecond Senſe.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Whether they have deſturb'd the World by Principles of Religion.</hi> This hath been ſo common a <hi>Theme</hi> of late years', that I need not ſpend much time in proving it. The Miter is by them exalted above the Crown; and <hi>Peter's</hi> pretended Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor is ſo far from Preaching up his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Subjection to the Civil Powers, that he requires Kings and Emperors to ſtoop to him. I need not laboriouſly prove this, by Quotations out of their Authors.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60423:66"/>
If the Decrees of their Councils, the Bulls of their Popes, the Determinations of their Canon-Law, the Aſſertions of not only Jeſuits (thoſe known Enemies to Monarchy) but of the moſt approv'd Doctors of all Orders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, may be taken to be the Senſe of their Church, the Learned Bp. of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> hath lately Collected them together; and thereby fully confirm'd the Title of his Book, That Popiſh Principles are deſtructive to Proteſtant Princes. There we may find ſuch dangerous Aſſertions as theſe, <hi>That Emperors and Kings are the Popes Subjects; That they may be depos'd by him for Schiſm, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Lazineſs, or unprofitableneſs; and that he is the ſole Judg of the Crime and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. That Statutes made by Laymen bind not the Clergy. That the Pope is the Vicar of God, and every creature is ſubject to him. That he that prefers the King before the Prieſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Creature before the Creator.</hi> In a word, He hath given ſuch convincing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, That King-killing Doctrines are authoriz'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> that we may juſtly wonder at the daring-Impudence of the late <hi>Tyburn</hi>-Saint, who pretended that none but <hi>Mariana</hi> ever publiſh'd ſuch Doctrines. But what truth can be ſo plain, which the Confidence of a Jeſuit dare not deny?
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60423:66"/>
Neither have theſe been the idle Speculations of the Schools, or the entertainment of the Cells and Cloyſters; but have been practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally maintain'd many hundred Years, and the Hiſtory of the Church for ſome Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is nothing elſe but a Tragical and Bloody Comment on this Doctrine. 'Tis hardly poſſible to mention one King (ſince <hi>Rome's</hi> riſe to her greatneſs) that hath been but coldly affected to the Catholick Cauſe, who hath not been ſcar'd by the Thunders of the Pope, and Rebellions of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance in the <hi>Fredericks,</hi> and <hi>Henry's</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> who were haraſs'd with continual Civil Wars and Confuſion; in the two <hi>Henry's</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> one whereof (<hi>Henry</hi> the third) was Murder'd by <hi>Jaque Clement,</hi> and the act commended in a ſet Oration, by Pope <hi>Sixtus quintus,</hi> and that execrable Murder compar'd to the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſurrection of our Lord; and the Virtue and Courage of the Fryer, to that of <hi>Judith</hi> and <hi>Eleazer.</hi> The other (<hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th</hi>) was as barbariouſly Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by <hi>Ravilliac.</hi> But I ſhall confine my ſelf to our own Land, and briefly ſhow how theſe men have turn'd our <hi>Engliſh</hi> World upſide down. Here I might inſtance
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60423:67"/>
in King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> and King <hi>John,</hi> who were both ſcar'd by the Popes Thunderbolts into mean Submiſſions, below the Dignity of Crowned heads, and the latter at laſt poyſon'd by a fawning Monk. But I ſhall only mention their villanous Practices, ſince the beginning of the Reformation; When King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> firſt renounc'd the Popes Supremacy, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> Curſes and Damns that King, and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Cites them to appear before him in ſixty Days; and upon their refuſal, ratifies this Excommunication; Prohibits them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian Burial, and declares them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally Damn'd; deprives that King of all his Dignities, and commands his Subjects to take up Arms, and compel him to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal the Law he had made. When Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came to the Crown, 'tis well known, how Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> depoſed her; and the Northern Rebellion, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſecret Plots by Poyſon, Gun-powder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to be read in our Chronicles; but when theſe deſigns prov'd unſuccesful, Pope <hi>Sixtus quintus,</hi> Publiſhes a <hi>Croiſade</hi> againſt her, and perſwades King <hi>Philip</hi> to War againſt her, and crowns his Fleet with the Title of the <hi>Invincible Armado;</hi> but the immediate hand of Heaven diſpers'd their
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60423:67"/>
Ships by Tempeſt, and thus confuted their proud conceits, and gave a Demonſtration to the World, that infallibility dwelt not at <hi>Rome;</hi> which made the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Admiral ſwear, he thought Jeſus Chriſt was turn'd <hi>Lutheran;</hi> but the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King ſaid more ſoberly, <hi>He ſent his Navy to fight againſt men, and not againſt God, to whoſe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Providence he attributed that Defeat.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter That Queen's Death, they us'd many Artifices to prevent King <hi>James</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Crown. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> ſent two Breivs into <hi>England,</hi> one to the Clergy, and another to the Laity, not to ſuffer any but a Catholick, tho never ſo near in Blood, to Succeed; and Father <hi>Parſons</hi> writ a Book to invalidate his Title, tho they had before Proclaim'd <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> the lawful Heir to the Kingdom. But when theſe attempts met not with their deſir'd Succeſs, they enter'd into that black unheard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Conſpiracy of the Powder-Treaſon; and tho now they pretend this was only a Plot of <hi>Cecil</hi>'s, to render them odious; yet we have full Confirmation of their Guilt, and may be aſſur'd the Pope would have reſented the welcome News of this Iſlands Reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tho by ſo bloody a means, to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> See, with as much joy as he ſince did the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60423:68"/>
hopes of rooting out this Northern Hereſie, when he <hi>wept for joy.</hi> And the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> would have been as great a Feſtival in their <hi>Calender,</hi> as now it is in ours. Nor were they leſs reſtleſs in their deſigns againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. 'Tis well known how they deſign'd to Murder that King, which was diſcover'd to Sir <hi>William Boſwel</hi> at the <hi>Hague.</hi> They fomented our differences, inflam'd the Spirits of men, and (acting their parts in ſeveral Diſguiſes) were the great Authors of our Civil Broils and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions. When that King was Impriſon'd by his unnatural Subjects, 'tis now publiſh'd to the World <note n="*" place="margin">See this and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in <hi>Dumoulins</hi> Anſwer to <hi>Phil. Ang.</hi>
               </note>, how a conſult of Prieſts and Jeſuits met at <hi>London,</hi> and in a Letter to the Drs. of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> ſent this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz. Whether conſidering the preſent poſture of Affairs, it were for the intereſt of the Catholick Cauſe to cut off that King, who remain'd obſtinate in his Hereſie?</hi> It was anſwer'd in the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive, and reſolv'd at <hi>Rome</hi> by the Pope and his Council, <hi>That it was not only Lawful, but Expedient.</hi> It cannot be deni'd, that too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſs'd Proteſtants did ingage in that barbarous Villany; but they had ſuck'd
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60423:68"/>
theſe poyſonous Principles, not from any Proteſtant Confeſſions of Faith, but <hi>Romiſh</hi> Canons and Decrees. Proteſtants diſown ſuch Principles; 'tis therefore an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing to accuſe the whole Party, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome Delinquents. But ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are authoriz'd and encourag'd by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Councils, as agreeable to their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We may be aſſur'd, the Ax that cut off our Sovereigns head, was whetted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romiſh Philiſtines;</hi> and whatever <hi>ſpurious Proteſtants</hi> join'd in that, or in any Treaſons of the like nature ſince that time, they were ſo far Papiſt, and belong not to us, but them. 'Twill but be needleſs labour to mention their ſecret Conſpiracies under our preſent Sovereign; the World hath been ſo fully inform'd about them. And I hope there is as little neceſſity of proving, that ſuch Practices are diſown'd by the Chriſtian Religion. For, muſt we <hi>pay unto Ceſar, the things that are Ceſars?</hi> And is Rebellion and Treaſon, the Tribute we owe him? Muſt every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers? And are Plots and Conſpiracies the beſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of our Allegiance? Are Conſecrated Knives and Daggers, any of our Goſpel-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery? and theſe Inſtruments of Death, our Weapons of Righteouſneſs? Surely that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60423:69"/>
that thus practically own Rebellions, is far different from what it was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles days, and it will be no Slander for us to ſay, <hi>Theſe are the men that have turned the world upſide down.</hi> I now proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <p>IV. <hi>What uſeful Inferences may be gather'd from our paſt Diſcourſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Hence we may ſee the excellence of the Proteſtant Religion. The Scripture is the ſole Rule of our Faith and Manners; pure and uncorrupted Chriſtianity reformed from the abuſive Additions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, is our Religion. We profeſs to own nothing as part of it, but what is (as to the eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als) ſummarily contain'd in the Baptiſmal Covenant, and more explicitely in the Creed, Lords Prayer, and ten Commandments, and (as to the Integrals) in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that whatever is ſaid in the former part of this Diſcourſe, to prove the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Chriſtian Inſtitution, doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually confirm the excellence of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faith, which is the very ſame with naked Chriſtianity. We believe the imcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibility and ſpirituality of Gods Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60423:69"/>
and dare not entertain any Images of him, no not in our very Imaginations. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels we Reverence as nobler and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Beings than our ſelves; but dare not pay them that Adoration which the Jealous God will not give to another. The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> we account bleſſed among Women, but dare not exalt her into the Throne of her Son, nor blaſphemouſly aſcribe Divine Prerogatives to her. The Holy Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, we reſpectfully remember, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to imitate them as they follow'd Chriſt; but dare not pray unto them, as if they were Omniſcient; nor give thoſe Services to them, which are appropriated to God and the Lord Jeſus. The Holy Sacrament we joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Celebrate, as a Seal of our Saviours tender Affection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But dare not Worſhip the Bread, <hi>but eat it in remembrance of</hi> him. We Worſhip God with the moſt comely out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Poſtures, and eſpecially with ſincere and ſpiritual Affection; but have no occaſion for the fooliſh Charms of the Heathens, or burdenſome Rites of the <hi>Jews.</hi> Our Lord Jeſus we acknowledg as our only Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal King and Sovereign; and whoever ſhall boldly alter his Laws, or invade his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, ſhall be rejected by us as an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. He is our only High Prieſt and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60423:70"/>
and let other men talk at what vain rates they will, we are better acquainted with our own Infirmities, than to plead any merit of our own. Through his Blood alone we hope for Salvation; and let others truſt in the merits of Saints, the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vertue of Medals and Relicks, and priviledg'd Altars, and ſuch like hallow'd Baubles: We will depend on nothing but his meritorious Sacrifice; leſt, when it is too late, we meet with a ſhameful diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and paſs out of this World, not into a temporary Purgatory, but an eternal Hell. Chriſts Prophetical Office we own, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to adjuſt our lives according to the Laws of the Goſpel. We teach the People to Study the Scripture daily, and to examine all our Doctrines by the Touchſtone of the Word. We acknowledg our ſelves to be fallible men, and ſhould very gladly return to the boſome of that Church that is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indued with a Spirit of Infallibility; but deſire better proofs, than thoſe vain and idle ones we have hitherto heard of. The Holy Laws of the Goſpel are our ſtanding-Rule; and tho others vainly diſtinguiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Duty, we will keep cloſe to theſe commands. Piety, Juſtice, and Charity, in their fulleſt extent, we own to be our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60423:70"/>
Duty, without thoſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gloſſes and Reſtrictions which ſome have invented. True uniform ſelf-denial, is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd as abſolutely neceſſary, and we place it not in uncommanded Auſterities; but in mortifying our Luſts, and ſubduing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever oppoſes the Glory of God, or our own Salvation. True undiſſembled Loyalty we acknowledg'd as our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Duty: Religion and Loyalty go hand in hand in our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; theſe are our Principles; and oh, that our Practices were univerſally like them. If we did but univerſally live up to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Principles we maintain, our Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples would be convincing, give ſuch a lovely Deſcription of our Religion, as would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Eyes, and convert the hearts of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and more ſuccesfully ſerve the Proteſtant intereſt, than all the Arguments in our Books. This leads to,</p>
            <p>2. Let our lives be agreeable to the Rules of our Religion. Let every one that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to Reformed Chriſtianity, live a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Life. Let not Religion only mend our heads, but our hearts too; and not only rectifie the errors and miſtakes of our Minds, but alſo the miſcarriages and offences of our Lives. For a profeſſed Proteſtant to lead
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60423:71"/>
a vicious life, is much more unbecoming and dangerous, than for thoſe who hope to be ſaved at an eaſier rate, and own a more looſe Religion. Tho we do know our Duty, except we practice it, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be happy. Let me intreat you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you have any concern for your ſelves, and your own intereſt; if you would not be accounted perjur'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, take heed how you contradict your Baptiſmal Vows, and many repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Engagements to forſake the World, and Fleſh, and Devil. If you would not lye under the Imputation of the moſt dangerous hypocriſie or unbelief, forbear thoſe Sins which are diſpleaſing to God, and forbidden by your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Not to believe the Chriſtian, or (which is the ſame) the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, after ſuch full Confirmation, is certainly very unreaſonable; but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heve it to be true, and yet to live as if it were falſe, is the greateſt Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Repugnancy imaginable. Do not you profeſs to believe, That <hi>without h lineſs, no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> and yet will you venture to continue in a ſinful courſe? Do you believe that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wilful Sinner ſhall be doom'd to Hell,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60423:71"/>
and all the Prayers and Tears of the holieſt men on Earth, can never fetch them thence; and yet will you continue in a ſtate of reſolved impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence? If you would not therefore that the Articles of your Faith ſhould be ſo many Articles of Accuſation againſt you at the great day, let your knowledg be improv'd into a Religious practice, and not only tend to aggravate your future miſery. Further, if you have any concern for the Religion you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and would not it ſhould be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd as an encouragement to wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; Now break off your Sins by Repentance and Amendment of Life; by our impure lives, we take the moſt effectual courſe in the World to bring our Religion it ſelf into diſgrace; and do more prejudice to the Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, than we can poſſibly advance it by our Arguments. I could there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore almoſt wiſh, That men would either diſown their Sins, or their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; openly renounce their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſtrictly comply with its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and if they will not be ſo generous as to follow its Directions, they would at leaſt be ſo honeſt, as to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60423:72"/>
quit their claim, rather than ſtill to retain it, only the more effectually to diſgrace the Religion they profeſs. Let thoſe that know no better, allow themſelves in ſin and wickedneſs; but let us that diſown their principles, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor, their lives too. Our God will not indulge us in wickedneſs; nor can we expect any diſpenſation <hi>from Heaven</hi> for our debaucheries and prophaneneſs; nay, further, if we would not provoke God to leave us, and ſuffer our ſubtil enemies to eſtabliſh their impure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, let us not imitate them in ſin: For if we become followers of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, God may in juſt judgment make them Lords of our Faith alſo. In a word, (to conclude with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of an excellent perſon) we have the beſt and holieſt, the wiſeſt and moſt reaſonable Religion in the World: but then we are in the worſt condition of all mankind, if the beſt Religion in the World do not make us good.</p>
            <p>3. Let us not by our diviſions let in our common enemy. Our ſends and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, and intemperate heats among our
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60423:72"/>
ſelves, are the ready way to bring in Popery into our Land. By our Diviſions we weaken our own Intereſt, imploy our pains and abilities in quarrelling about trifles, and diſable our ſelves in a great meaſure from preventing the growth and increaſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion. By our Diviſions we expoſe our ſelves to the United Power of our Common Adverſaries; and like the unhappy <hi>Jews</hi> of old, we are ſquabling among our ſelves, while the <hi>Romans</hi> are ready to enter in upon us at thoſe wide breaches we have made for them. By our Diviſions, we become acceſſary to our own ruin; and have great reaſon to fear, leſt we do that with our own hands, which all the Policies of <hi>Rome</hi> have not hitherto been able to effect. By our Diviſions we may provoke God to ſuffer our enemies to prevail; and by fiery trials to ſcourge us into Love and Unity. Then we ſhall too late repent of our violence and bitterneſs: And when we ſadly look back, and reflect how happy once we might have been, this will be no mean aggravation of our miſery. And when we remember we brought our afflictions upon our ſelves, we ſhall have cauſe to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60423:73"/>
ſay, with ſad hearts; and tears in our eyes: <hi>Oh that we had known the things that belong to our Peace.</hi> Let us now therefore be intreated to lay aſide preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and paſſion, and have greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the common good, than the intereſt of any particular Party. Let us more impartially weigh the differences among our ſelves, and reſolve that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſin ſhall hinder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a full agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And by mutual compliances 'tis no impoſſible thing to be reconcil'd: But if that be too great a bleſſing for ſuch a ſinful People, and there muſt be differences among us, Oh that we could once learn to differ in judgment, without any alienation of affections. That we could once learn, that the Kingdom of God is not meat and drink, conſiſts not in ſuch little things as are the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our difference; But in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouneſs and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. And he that leads an holy Life, ſhall be accepted by God, tho he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip not him after our particular mode, and prehaps be guilty of ſome miſtakes. Are not our differences much of the ſame nature with thoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. And why ſhould not his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60423:73"/>
be carefully obſerv'd? Why ſhould we aggravate every little difference, or height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en every ſmall miſtake, or cenſoriouſly condemn one another as Hypocrites, becauſe (tho we agree in all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials of Religion) we cannot be all of a mind, in ſome particular forms, and modes, and ceremonies? Are not we all fallible creatures? and ſhall we be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at our brethren for that which is the common condition of Men? May not the error be on our own ſide as well as our Brothers? And is this becoming a Chriſtian, or an ingenuous man, to condemn another for that wherein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I may be guilty my ſelf? We cannot gratify the Papiſts more, than by theſe unhappy diſputes. Let us therefore by the friendſhip we bear to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Intereſt, by the concern we have for our Religion, and juſt hatred we bear to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, be perſwaded, either wholly to lay aſide, or at leaſt to be more moderate and calm in our differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Let us labour after Healing, Uniting Spirits; imploy our zeal about the great Duties of Religion; ſtrive which ſhall be the beſt Chriſtians and the beſt Subjects; and leave the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60423:74"/>
Diſputes about leſſer things, to thoſe who know not how better to imploy their time: Then we need not fear the attempts of our enemies: And as God hath hitherto, ſo we may hope he will ſtill be our great defender. But (as one ſays very well) till we are as zealous againſt the Antichriſts in our own breaſts, as Pride, Anger, Malice, and Bitterneſs, as againſt him that ſits in the <hi>Roman</hi> Chair, and learn heartily to love one another, we have little reaſon to hope with <hi>Agag,</hi> that the bitterneſs of Death is paſt: but have too much cauſe to dread the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Yoak.</p>
            <p>4. Let us never Apoſtatize to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion. A Religion which perfectly overturns Chriſtianity, and abſolutely overthrows all Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A Religion which deſtroys our duty to our Heavenly, and diſſolves our obligation to our Earthly Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign. A Religion that takes away that fear of God which Chriſtianity obliges us to; and denies that honour to the King which the Law of Nature and the Light of Revelation binds upon us.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60423:74"/>
If we would perform a more reaſonable ſervice than Heathens offer, let us not return to the ſorceries and charms of <hi>Rome.</hi> If we have any reſpect to the Commands of God, or dread Divine threatnings, let us not deny him that Spiritual Worſhip he requires, nor fall down before Graven Images; Except we can be content with a Catechiſm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Second Commandment; a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament without the Cup; and a Bible which we cannot underſtand. Except we will Worſhip we know not what; Pray unto thoſe that cannot hear us; and truſt in thoſe that cannot help us. Except we can be content with a Faith without knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; a Hope without foundation; and a Charity that damns all the World but our ſelves: Till we can be perſwaded, That there may be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion without underſtanding; Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance without amendment; and Salvation without any labour or great induſtry to obtain it: Till we can be ſatisfi'd in theſe and all the other particulars I have mention'd, we cannot be thorow Papiſts. And if theſe things are not prejudice enough againſt that Church, it's a ſign we little underſtand what Religion
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60423:75"/>
means. Let us therefore ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on theſe particulars, that our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of Popery may not meerly be, becauſe we were educated in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Faith, and 'tis a faſhionable thing to rail againſt the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but it may be eſtabliſh'd upon firm and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble principles, ſuch as may endure a ſtorm and fiery trial, which (God knows) whether we may not be viſited with. That we may never run ſuch hazards of our Salvation, as we ſhall incur if we Apoſtatize to that Church. For how far the depths of Gods mercy may reach, and his ſovereign goodneſs may ſave a Natural Born Papiſt, I know not; how far their ignorance and prejudice may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them, is not for me to diſpute: But this I will ſay, If any who have been educated in the Proteſtant Faith, and well underſtood the Grounds of that Religion, ſhall turn Papiſt, he muſt have a great meaſure of charity who can think ſuch an one in any near proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Salvation. Let us therefore hold faſt our Religion, and ſtrictly comply with its excellent commands; let our profeſſions be ſincere, and our lives obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient; then, tho our enemies do plot
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60423:75"/>
our ruin, the God of Heaven will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear on our ſide; and his never-ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring Providence defeat their deſigns. <hi>Tho theſe who have turn'd the world upſide down ſhould come hither,</hi> yet their policies ſhall not prevail; But only give freſh occaſion to us to glorify God the Author of our Deliverance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:76"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>John Gellibrand,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>BOnetti Sepulchretum ſive Anatomia Practica, <hi>2 Vol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Mercurius competalitius ſive index Medico-Practicus.</item>
               <item>—Medicina Septentrionalis Collatitia. Baudrandi Geographia Ordina litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum diſpoſita, <hi>2 Vol.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diacus Medico-Gallicus, <hi>3 Vol.</hi> &amp; pro 3 Annis.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60423:76"/>Binchii Mellificium Theologicum.</item>
               <item>Theſes Salmurienſes, <hi>2 Vol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Sedanenſes, <hi>2 Vol.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>Sir <hi>John Temples Iriſh</hi> Rebellion.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Willian Temples</hi> Obſervations on the united <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—<hi>Miſcellanea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s Morals, Tranſlated from the <hi>Greek</hi> by ſeveral hands, in 3 Vol.</item>
               <item>Biſhp. <hi>Wilkins,</hi> of Prayer and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>—Sermons, and Beauty of Providence.</item>
               <item>—World in the Moon, and Earth a Planet.</item>
               <item>—Mathematical Magick.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Fords</hi> Expoſition upon the Church Catechiſm.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Jacomb</hi>'s Perſonal and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Dedication.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Duodecimo.</head>
               <item>Herles <hi>Wiſdoms Tripos.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Garbut, <hi>on the Reſurrection.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60423:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Virgil,</hi> cum notis Minellii.</item>
               <item>Florus cum notis Minellii.</item>
               <item>Tentamen Medicum de Varioris.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Old Mr. <hi>Dods</hi> ſayings in one large Sheet.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60423:77"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
